<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A practical discourse of silence and submission shewing that good men should possess their souls in patience under the severest providences : and particularly in the loss of dear relations : preached at St. Thomas's Hospital, Southwark / by William Hughes ...</title>
            <author>Hughes, William, b. 1624 or 5.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3345</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2599</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11781952</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11781952</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49116</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49116)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 537:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A practical discourse of silence and submission shewing that good men should possess their souls in patience under the severest providences : and particularly in the loss of dear relations : preached at St. Thomas's Hospital, Southwark / by William Hughes ...</title>
                  <author>Hughes, William, b. 1624 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 83 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Onely, for J. Salusbury ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49116:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49116:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Practical DISCOURSE OF <hi>Silence and Submiſſion:</hi> SHEWING, <hi>That Good MEN</hi> SHOULD Poſſeſs their Souls in PATIENCE UNDER THE Severeſt Providences, And particularly <hi>In the Loſs of Dear Relations.</hi> Preached at St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Hoſpital, <hi>Southwark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHES,</hi> Hoſpitaler there.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Shall we receive Good at the hand of God, and ſhall we not receive Evil?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job 2.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Peſſimi est Debitoris Creditore faceri convitium.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Sen. de Conſ. ad Mart. c. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Onely,</hi> for <hi>I. Salusbury,</hi> at the Riſing-Sun in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49116:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:49116:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful, <hi>Sir</hi> Robert Clayton, <hi>Kt.</hi> Alderman of the City of <hi>London,</hi> AND Preſident of St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Hoſpital, in <hi>Southwark.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">To the Worſhipful, James Reading, <hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </hi> Treaſurer of the ſaid Hoſpital. AND <hi>To the rest of the Right Worſhipful, Worſhipful, and Worthy</hi> Governours <hi>of the ſame.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Right Worſhipful,</hi> &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE <hi>Divine Preacher</hi> tells us; <hi>'Tis better to go the Houſe of Mourning, than to the Houſe of Feaſting.</hi> And there
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:49116:3"/>is indeed great reaſon for his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo. 'Tis ſomething, that this <hi>latter</hi> place commonly leaves Men Vainer, than it finds them. But 'tis a weighty one that he is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs in: the <hi>former; That, is, the end of all Men, and the living will lay it to heart.</hi> It ſhews; What all muſt come to: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the need of being prepared accordingly. Now, that my Lot is fallen in a great Family of greater Sorrows, altho it be your greateſt Care to turn thoſe into the Speedieſt Joys; is no Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity to affirm. I'm ſure, beſides the ſad Calamities of our Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, the Experience of my ſmall Apartment hath for theſe two Years paſt, by frequent and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Sickneſs, and by Death late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, met with loud Knels of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs.
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:49116:3"/>Nor may we doubt, but that many of your ſelves, ſome time or other, have heard ſuch doleful Leſſons. Nay, who can tell, how ſoon thoſe, yet exempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, may taſte of the ſame Bitter Cup; and perhaps drink deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it? So that a Diſcourſe, adapted to ſuch Circumſtances, cannot be unſeaſonable. Eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if it reſpect Preventing, Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting, Delivering thence, and making wiſe Improvement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. All which Advantages theſe Papers aim at: and, it is hoped, do not utterly miſs their Mark.</p>
            <p>Unto your Worſhips, the <hi>Eſſay,</hi> ſuch as 'tis, is moſt humbly dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated: as to It's Author's Patrons; and moſt worthy of more Honour than is within his reach to pay you. To forbear (tho not forget)
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:49116:4"/>your kind Reſpect unto Himſelf: nor to inſiſt upon the moſt <hi>Signal,</hi> but <hi>Secret,</hi> Charities of ſeveral of you, unto many hundred Pounds, (which, <hi>tho you would not have your left hand know what your right hand did,</hi> could not be quite concealed; indeed, <hi>ſuch Rare Examples ought not):</hi> Your Joint Compaſſion, and Tender Care of the Many Poor in this Great Hoſpital, proclaim your Merit, hardly <hi>Imitable;</hi> I'm ſure, truly <hi>Admirable!</hi> For, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides your Conſtant Proviſion of the Beſt Food, and Phyſick, and Surgery, that you can get; with very meet, both Firing, Lodging, and Attendance, you are now <hi>New-building of their Houſe;</hi> and at the vaſt Expence of many Thouſand Pounds. Whereby, at once you prevent their being Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:49116:4"/>Alive in the Ruins of an Old-decayed-Place; and likewiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for, Better-Preſerving Life, and Sooner-Reſtoring Health, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, by a far more <hi>Airy, Sweet,</hi> and <hi>Pleaſant Dwelling,</hi> than before they had: or ever could have ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for, <hi>But from <hi>Your Selves.</hi>
               </hi> That the God of Mercy, who firſt inclined you, may preſerve and proſper you, to the finiſhing of this Earthly Tabernacle for his Poor; and, in due ſeaſon, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward you with an <hi>Habitation not made with hands, Eternal in the Heavens,</hi> is the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Right Worſhipful,</hi> &amp;c.</salute> 
               <signed> 
                  <hi>Your very Hamble Servant,</hi> W. Hughes, <hi>Hoſpitaler.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:49116:5"/>
            <head>To my Beloved Friends, THE Officers and Patients, OF St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s <hi>Hoſpital,</hi> in <hi>Southwark.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Calamities of this Houſe in general, and the particular Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes of most of us, call aloud upon us, to ſeek a <hi>Refuge from the Storm;</hi> at least, to get <hi>ſome</hi> Shelter, till it be over. My hopes are, that theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons will ſomewhat Contribute to thoſe Ends; if due Regard be had unto them. And tho' mine own Afflictions were their Midwife; yet, being thus brought forth, they may be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful unto Others alſo. I ſhould be very glad to do you Good from the Preſs; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo many of you ſlight my Service
<pb facs="tcp:49116:5"/>from the Pew, and Pulpit. For to my Grief I ſpeak it, 'tis very doubtful, whether a fifth Part of you (that can) be conſtant at the Chappel. 'Twas altogether otherwiſe in the former Years of my Miniſtry here. And I am ſure, my <hi>Pains</hi> are nothing abated: but my <hi>Judgment</hi> ſomewhat improved ſince. But <hi>then</hi> indeed we had the Happineſs of a Steward, who made Conſcience of the Duty of his Place; and did not only duly come himſelf, but brought Others with him; and puniſhed thoſe who, cauſeleſsly, abſented. And I am fully of Opinion, that True Religion was as thriving then among as, as ever is hath been ſince. Do not <hi>our Publick Orders</hi> tell all Officers here (as well as Patients;) that, <hi>without reaſonable Excuſe,</hi> they mst be conſtant at the Publick Worſhip? And doth not every Officer <hi>Enter</hi> on his Place upon thoſe Terms? Can it be <hi>Conſcience</hi> then; to take the Wages, and not do the Work? Will not <hi>That</hi> ſay; let alone the Salary, or buckle to the Service? How many, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, are never preſent? So vain a <hi>Coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> with ſome, and vile <hi>Prophaneſs</hi> with others, hath of late times prevailed among us! Were there just Quarrel at the Publick Prayers; (as I know no Perſon with us,
<pb facs="tcp:49116:6"/>that hath any; or juſtly can have;) must Sermons ſuffer for that, however? Hath <hi>Any</hi> a Grudge against the Miniſter? Surely a Wiſe Man will not ſullenly leave his Food, becauſe the Cook hath angred him? But if the Bread of Life be given you here; and you refuſe it: is not the <hi>Giver,</hi> more contemned, than he that brings it? Beware of their most heavy Guilt; <hi>whoſe Souls</hi> (they ſaid) <hi>loathed that light Bread.</hi> For that was ſpoken against <hi>God,</hi> as well as <hi>Moſes, Num. 21.5.</hi> Tho, you are told expreſly; to <hi>Deſpiſe,</hi> or <hi>not to Hear</hi> (which are both One) a Goſpel-Miniſter, is ſerving <hi>both the Son and Father too,</hi> at the ſelf-ſame rate, <hi>Luke 10.16.</hi> If a very few can plead, <hi>Their Relations elſe-where,</hi> in their own Defence. Why? Without med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the Merits of the Cauſe; (and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide what was ſaid about twenty lines before) Is not the Plea as good; to juſtifie an hungry Man's Refuſal of wholeſome Food at his loving Neighbour's; becauſe, forſooth it was not ſet upon his own Table, where he did uſe to Eat? Let us be faithful to our Souls. Is not the want of Spiritual Appetite, our great Diſtemper? Did we <hi>hunger, thirſt,</hi> and <hi>long</hi> for God: would we be ſo Coy, as to meet him only <hi>where</hi> we pleaſe; and <hi>when</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:49116:6"/>ourſelves think ſitting? Surely we would be glad at any place, and as often as we could, to enjoy his bleſſed Company in his holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances. We ſhould <hi>flock as Doves to our Windows:</hi> and the <hi>Feet of them that bring glad Tydings,</hi> whoever they were, would be beautiful in our Eyes. Were we ſo ſenſibly affected, as we ſhould be, with our weak Faith, chill Love, faint Hope, earthly Mind, and ſtrong Corruptions; the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities for quickning Graces, and killing Luſts now neglected, if not deſpiſed, would be more welcome to us; and be with greater Diligence improved by us. But if a <hi>Form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without the Power</hi> be all we mind (ſo, 'tis with thouſands:) as that will eaſily ſerve with Men, tho' not with God; ſo 'tis no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, that our ſorry Humours, and not ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſcience, ſteer our Courſe for us. Well: <hi>Manna lies abundantly about our Tents</hi> at preſent: but it may ſo happen (I'm ſure our Sins deſerve it) that ſuch Scraps as theſe, now reckon'd only worthy to be thrown under Table, may e're long be accounted Dainties. Black Clouds are over us: Diſtreſſes near us: Grim Death, most certainly is not far from us. O that we may be Wiſe, and husband ſo that little inch of Time
<pb facs="tcp:49116:7"/>yet left, in true Chriſtian Praying, Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Reading, Meditation, and holy Walking, that we may be prepared for a Bleſſed Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: This is the hearty Deſire of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Souls Faithful, and <hi>Truth-telling</hi> Friend, <hi>W. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. l. 9. for <hi>3dly,</hi> r. <hi>2dly,</hi> p. 10. l. 29. after <hi>thought,</hi> a Period. p. 15. l. 23. r. <hi>Impatience.</hi> p. 18. l. 10. r. <hi>afflicted</hi> for <hi>affected.</hi> p. 20. l. 23. after <hi>them,</hi> Coma. p. 33. l. 5. r. <hi>Blood.</hi> p. 39. l. 19. after <hi>it,</hi> r. <hi>ſelf.</hi> p. 41. l. 5. after <hi>Bar,</hi> r. <hi>thereto.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49116:7"/>
            <head>A Practical Diſcourſe ON <hi>The Severeſt Providences,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM XXXIX. ix.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>I was dumb, I opened not my mouth; becauſe thou, Lord didst it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>MAn is born unto trouble,</hi> (ſaith holy <hi>Job) as the ſparks fly upwards;</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly is the nature of them. And to the certain truth of that Aſſertion, Towas, Cities, and Courts; in Pagan, Tunkiſh, and Chriſtian Countries, do ever and anon bear ample Teſtimony. For there is neither Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Age, nor Sex of Mortals can plead a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, to be exempted thence. But, of all other Men, the <hi>truly Pions</hi> have the moſt cauſe to expect their ſhare therein; and leaſt reaſon, <hi>truly,</hi> to complain thereof. That bleſſed Book, whereto they are not ſtrangers, as others are, informs them; that it is their Lot, <hi>to have their Evil things here, and their Good hereafter.</hi> But, the mean while, 'tis far from juſtifing their raiſing Mole-hills into Mountains; and making of their Troubles a great deal worſer than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are. Nay, it condemneth, juſtly, and ſeverely, <hi>Laying the Products of their own
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49116:8"/>Follies to the Fault of God;</hi> as if he dealt not fairly by them, when, in truth, 'tis they fall ſoul upon themſelves; both in the bringing, and the bearing all they ſuffer.</p>
            <p>Now, having often ſeen this guilt too much abroad; and being myſelf more than once, (ſo it hath ſeemed meet to the Righteous Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) in danger of plunging into the ſame Gulf; I held it neceſſary for the Common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Chriſtianity, <hi>as well as my own,</hi> to make Enquiry after, and to ſind out the means, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by good People may recover from, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe into, a caſe ſo dangerous. My thoughts then, being once upon Enquiry, ſoon lighted on this welcome Text. And truly, 'tis an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Remedy! which alſo I nothing doubt, will prove ſucceſsful where 'tis duly uſed. The Uſe whereof, I think, ſhould be according to the Method my following Diſcourſe preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Context.</hi>] The Pſalm doth plainly manifeſt, that its Author, <hi>David,</hi> was la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring under a very ſore Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Chryſ. Calv. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Whether it aroſe from <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Sickneſs,</hi> as ſome have thought, or the <hi>Rebellion of his Darling, Abſalon,</hi> as others are of Opinion, or from any other Cauſe, (as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny might be gues'd at) ſince none's expres'd; to make ſtrict Search about it, would ſavour more of fruitleſs Curioſity, than of uſeful Induſtry; and in the Iſſue, leave us at Uncertainty too. This he, that runneth through the whole, may
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49116:8"/>quickly read, as written there, in Capital Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>That there was ſuch a Storm</hi> (from whence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it roſe) <hi>that had like to have ſhipwrack'd all.</hi> It ſeems, as if the Rigging were torn in peices, the Hull ſhrewdly ſhatter'd, and the Fraight likewiſe in manifeſt jeopardy to periſh in the Deep. The Afflicted, in Spirit, Soul, and Body, to all appearance, receiv'd no little Dammage by the ſame. For Proof whereof, 'twere very eaſy to offer ſeveral Inſtances from the Pſalm, would it not be too tedious parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to inſiſt upon them.</p>
            <p>However, ſomething muſt appear in view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Parts thereof: which are theſe two in general:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Pſalmiſt's Procedure with himſelf, under his great Affliction; and that in the two firſt Verſes; reſumed alſo in my Text.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Effects of that Procedure with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon him, in the following Verſes, even to the end.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the former: The courſe he takes (as you may read) is, to ſeal his Lips, and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence his Heart too. That not a Word might ſlip from <hi>thence</hi> to ſhew one diſcontented Thought towards God <hi>there.</hi> Thus he ſtops his Mouth, and ſtills his Mind at once; that no Complaint, or any Murmure might be with him againſt the Divine Providence, for the ſeverer Methods uſed towards him. But yet (Good Man) herein it hapned unto him, as it ſometimes may to the beſt Archer in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49116:9"/>World; who to prevent his Arrow's falling ſhort, levels ſo high, that he over-ſhoots his Mark. For the Holy Pſalmiſt alſo (though to his Grief) doth over-do his Work for a little while. <hi>He held his peace from good:</hi> but thence <hi>his ſorrow was ſtirred,</hi> Verſe 2. latter end. But the ſault is ſoon amended, by the new Aim he takes. As will be ſeen by,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Fruit of his thus dealing with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: which, truly, was not to be repented of. And 'twas two fold:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Internal.</hi> All Complaints, and Repinings too, againſt God's <hi>Juſtice</hi> being ſtifled, his Meditations are ſet warm at work upon his <hi>Mercy:</hi> Thoſe raiſe his paſſionate Deſires af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, and they force their paſſage through his Lips unto him. <hi>His heart was hot, the fire burnt;</hi> and then his Tongue ſtood ſtill no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Verſe 3. <hi>Then ſpake I with my tongue,</hi> ſaith he. Thus comes the other Effect.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>External. viz.</hi> Hearty Prayer unto the juſt and gracious God, made up of three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticlar Petitions firſt; and then a general one, as the Concluſion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He begs particularly: 1. For an affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sence of his Frailty and Vanity: <hi>Make me to know mine end,</hi> &amp;c. Verſe 4. And pleadeth humbly for Succeſs herein, to Ver. 8.2. Then for <hi>pardon of his ſin,</hi> Ver. 8. <hi>Deliver me from all my tranſgreſſions,</hi> &amp;c. Uſing my Text for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of his Suit. And laſtly, He prays <hi>Deliverance</hi> from his Afflictions alſo: <hi>Remove
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49116:9"/>thy ſtroke,</hi> &amp;c. Ver. 10, 11. urging for pity; both the Load that lay upon him, and his, and all others, Inability to ſtand up under Divine Diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He concludeth with a general Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for a gracious Anſwer to his former Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions: and for prevailing, repreſents his ſad Condition as a moſt ſuitable Object of Divine Compaſſion, Ver. 12, 13.</p>
            <p>But I muſt return to the ſecond particular Petition; whereto I did obſerve, my Text was added as an Enforcement of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David,</hi> Ver. 8. begging pardon for his Sins, which were the cauſe of all his Troubles; and which, particularly, made wicked Men to open their mouths againſt him; begging pardon, as I was ſaying, in theſe words, <hi>Deliver me from all my tranſgreſſions, and make me not the reproach of the fooliſh;</hi> now, that this humble Suit might ſpeed the better, readily yields, and plainly enough makes this Confeſſion: <q>That notwithſtanding their Reproaches, as well as all his other Troubles, were moſt unjuſt from Men; yet they came not without the juſteſt reaſon <hi>from the Lord</hi> upon him. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had not one Word to ſpeak, nor Thought to think, againſt the ſame: <hi>I was dumb,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I opened not my mouth,</hi> &amp;c.</q> 
            </p>
            <p>Thus ſtands the Text in relation to the Context: But if we conſider it in its ſelf, then it gives us,</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49116:10"/>
            <p n="1">1. A ſreſh Account of <hi>David's</hi> Carriage un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his great Diſtreſſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The important Reaſon why he did ſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The former <hi>here: I was dumb, I opened not my mouth,</hi> where the latter Phraſe aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth higher than that before it. <hi>Both</hi> import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing plainly; that as he did not ſpeak at all, ſo he never ſo much as offer'd it neither. Yea, and the <hi>Hebrew Verb,</hi> in the latter Clauſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Future Tenſe doth intimate, that he would not ever make any ſuch attempt in time to come. And this demonſtrates the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute ſilence and perfect ſatisfaction his Soul was brought unto under that heavy Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, whatever it was, that lay upon him. For as when the Waves don't ſwell the Winds are ſtill; ſo when the Mouth makes no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, the Heart doth <hi>uſe</hi> to be at reſt. And 'tis our Saviour's ſaying, <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh,</hi> Matth. 12.34.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The latter part is <hi>there: Becauſe thou, Lord, didst it.</hi> As who ſhould ſay, <q>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever influence <hi>ſecond Cauſes</hi> may have had immediately upon my preſent Troubles, and whatever Imputation I may juſtly lay on Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or on Things, for what I ſuffer, I muſt not here abide, but paſs on further, through them and beyond them, to the <hi>first Cauſe</hi> of all: <hi>Thou, Lord, didst it.</hi>
               </q> This was like holy <hi>Job;</hi> who, for all the miſchief <hi>Satan,</hi> the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49116:10"/>and <hi>Sabeans</hi> wickedly did him, looks higher to the righteous Hand of God, and humbly bows before him, ſaying, <hi>The Lord giveth, and the Lord taketh away; and bleſſed be the Name of the Lord,</hi> Job 1.21. We ſee Good Men are utterly unlike the ſottiſh Cur, which ſnarleth at the Stone that hits him, until he dangers breaking of his Teeth in gnawing it, without regard unto the Hand that threw it. The Ungodly commonly are thus guilty; and are reproved juſtly by the Prophet for it, <hi>Lord, when thy hand is lifted up, they will not ſee,</hi> Iſai. 26.11. But the Pious practiſe otherwiſe, as we find; and thence find alſo cauſe to ſtoop to God, and <hi>poſſeſs their Souls in patience</hi> under all their Sufferings. And that there is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient reaſon ſo to do, we ſhall ſee anon; when, beſides all other Arguments, it will appear par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, what a prevailing influence the <hi>lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> part of my Text hath on the <hi>former.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In order whereunto, ſince there is juſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, that this great Example is obliging to all other Perſons in like Circumſtances, let this Propoſition ſeriouſly be conſidered by us, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Propoſ.] <hi>A Godly Perſon is to be ſtill and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and by no means impatient under the heaviest Hand of God upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Propoſition being plain, and very intelligible in all the Terms thereof, we have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49116:11"/>only need of, 1. A further Confirmation of it. 2. A fair Solution of ſome Objections. 3. and lastly, Some Guidance for the better Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the whole unto our ſelves for good. Whereof in order. And,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1st,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Proof, by Examples and Arguments.</note> To make full Proof, I ſhall produce two kinds of Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, <hi>viz.</hi> Plain Examples, and Powerfal Arguments, and with a good ſtock of both from the Holy Scriptures. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with <hi>Plain Examples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Examples.</hi>] They ſhall be Seven or Eight, and every one well deſerving ſpecial Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>I will take them in that order the Scriptures ſet them: And ſo begin with,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Moſes.</hi> That the moſt wiſe and gracious Providence ſaw meet to exerciſe this moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Saint with various Tryals, and ſome that had much ſharpneſs in them, the Book of God bears ample teſtimony: nor is it ſilent about that even and quiet Temper wherein his Soul was preſerved under them. The danger of his Life from the hands of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> at his firſt appearance, in one of his Brethrens cauſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an <hi>Egyptian,</hi> made him to fly the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for his fafety. But he<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 11.27</note> 
               <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured it,</hi> ſaith the Text, and left no Murmuring nor Complaints behind him; no, nor carried he any with him,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49116:11"/>that we can ſind, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.15. His Brethren likewiſe often dealt ſo unkindly by him, and their Inſolencies towards him (not withſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his moſt conſtant and tender concernment for them) were ſo inſufferable, that the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God doth eſpouſe the quarrel, and is provoked to deſtroy them, root and branch, for the ſame. Yea, and he promiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> to make of him a Nation mightier and greater than they were, if he would conſent thereto. But he, good Man,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.10, 11.</note> bears all with patience from <hi>Them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 11.17, 19.</note> and is moſt inſtant with <hi>God</hi> for ſaving of them;<note place="margin">Deut. 9.18, &amp;c.</note> and ſo requites them good for evil. Why, tho'<note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 26.59.</note> 
               <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam,</hi> that came out of the ſame Womb with him, <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted and reviled him,</hi> (unjuſtly we are ſure, becauſe God was offended with them highly for the ſame) yet he takes it quietly; and <hi>begs,</hi> and <hi>procures God's pardon to them for it,</hi> Numb. 12.9, 13. Nay, when the Wiſe of his Boſom taunts him to his face, and at the ſame time the Face of God was frowning on him alſo, yet is he the ſame Man ſtill, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.24, 25.</p>
            <p>Should not <hi>we</hi> think, that theſe were none of them ſlight Afflictions, tho' ſome more ſharp than others? Would they not eaſily warp <hi>us</hi> to impatience under them? But as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, That he was <hi>the meekest man upon the face of the earth,</hi> Numb. 12.3; doubtleſs 'twas
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49116:12"/>meant, that he was not only ſo <hi>towards Men, but towards God alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, you ſhall yet hear greater things than theſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Aaron,</hi> 'Tis true, he had great Frailties in him, and like Afflictions on him; but ſtill he hath this excellent Character given him, <hi>The ſaint of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 106.16. Now this Saint hath a bloody Breach made by an angry God upon his Family, and not for any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Crime of his neither; nay, the Method was not uſual, but extraordinary, and full of terrour: His Sons make a <hi>daring,</hi> but it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a <hi>dear,</hi> Adventure. They <hi>offered ſtrange fire before the Lord;</hi> and a more ſtrange <hi>fire from the Lord falls down upon them, and devoured them,</hi> Levit. 10.1, 2, 3. Fire, in it ſelf, is a very furious and frightful Element; but this, being not <hi>the fire that burned in the buſh, and burnt it not,</hi> Exod. 3.2, 3. nor that which carried up <hi>Elijah</hi> into Heaven; ſo far from hurting him, as making of him happy, and putting him out of the reach of Hurt for ever: No, <hi>but a fire from the Lord,</hi> ſaith the Text; who <hi>is a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire,</hi> Heb. 12.29: eſpecially to bold Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders; that are as dried Stubble before him. This offers one terrible Circumſtance to our thoughts, Moreover, this Fire falls down, not upon the good Man, <hi>Aaron</hi>'s, Houſe, or Goods, or Cattel; any of which might have had dread enough therein: but on his <hi>Children,</hi> on his <hi>Sons,</hi> his Sons that were <hi>God's Miniſters;</hi> nor
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49116:12"/>upon <hi>one</hi> alone, but <hi>two</hi> at once: not in the <hi>Fields,</hi> or in a private <hi>Houſe,</hi> where poſſibly it might have been concealed, at leaſt but little notice taken of it: but in the <hi>Tabernacle;</hi> and at God's <hi>Publick Worſhip;</hi> and in <hi>their Miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> there; and before the face of <hi>all the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</hi> Here is an heap of Circumſtances, not one of which but carrieth horrour and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment with it: but <hi>all, together,</hi> are utterly confounding. Well, but hereupon how doth the good, but ſad Father, behave himſelf? What? Doth he fret, and fume, and vex his Soul to death again? No, no. Doth he rage, and rave, and flie in the face of God upon it? 'Twas further from him. <hi>Jehoram</hi>'s great, but wicked Meſſenger, in a time of Diſtreſs, would ſay, <hi>This evil is of the Lord; why ſhould we wait for the Lord any longer?</hi> 2 Kings 6.33. He bids adieu to God; and let him find ſome other At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants, if he pleaſe. <hi>Job</hi>'s naughty Wife would have prompted him to relieve himſelf, by <hi>curſing God, and dying together with his ſons,</hi> Job 2.9. But this <hi>pious Perſon</hi> was of another ſpirit: ſor ſaith the Text, <hi>Aaron held his peace.</hi> His ſilent Soul ſeal'd up his lips; and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of his heart kept his mouth cloſe ſhut. He knew <hi>who did it:</hi> and to undo God's Work, ſo much as by a <hi>word</hi> or <hi>thought;</hi> no Creature ought to make one attempt. The leaſt diſlike abetted, bids all (in Humane reach) unto it: No, when God hath done, he will not begin, but end together with him, and be moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49116:13"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to him, <hi>He held his peace.</hi> A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and well worth the writing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> next, and againſt this good old Man (though under much Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity) the Almighty dips his Pen in Gaul and Vinegar.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.11 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> And truly they are ſharp and bitter things that are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the ſacred Book againſt him, and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily with him. 'Tis not the pruning Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or lopping off ſome greater Boughs; but 'tis the digging up by the very Roots, that is inſiſted on. And for his full aſſurance, he muſt be certified once and again there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.<note place="margin">Chap. 2, &amp; 3.</note> Firſt by a nameleſs <hi>Prophet,</hi> and then by his Darling-pupil, <hi>Samuel.</hi> The former tells him from the mouth of God, that, <hi>The days come that I will cut off thine arm, and the arm of thy father's houſe; and there ſhall not be an old man in thine houſe for ever,</hi> Chap. 2.31, 32. with much more terrible Tydings beſides this. And the <hi>latter,</hi> That <hi>God would perform against Eli all things which he had ſpoken concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his houſe; and that he would judge it for ever,</hi> Chap. 3.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with other Threats like thoſe. Well now: how doth this aged Father enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the doleful News? Doth he diſpatch the Meſſenger that brought ſuch unwelcome Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings? Or ſo much as wiſh unto him <hi>Micaiah</hi>'s <hi>Doom</hi> from wicked <hi>Ahab, To be clapt in goal, and be fed with bread and water of affliction?</hi> Doth he curſe his harder Fates, whereby he was chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49116:13"/>unto ſuch unavoidable Miſery; and like the <hi>Deſperate</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Qui, manu ſanguine ſuo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleta, &amp; in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it; <hi>Viciſti Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilaee.</hi> Theed. Hiſt. <hi>4.25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Julian,</hi> go off the Earth with bidding a Defiance to the God of Heaven? As much unlike thoſe Tempers, as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is unto Hell. 'Tis taken by him without the leaſt Complaint; and without ſo much as any To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Regret. If you feel his Pulſe, there's nothing of a Feavour on him. The very Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants of Impatience are driven into Exile by him. Hear his own words, <hi>It is the Lord; let him do what ſeemeth him good,</hi> Verſe 18. As who ſhould ſay, <q>All are his own, and he may, therewithal, and ought to do what is beſt pleaſing to himſelf. Who are we, entire De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants on him, to call him to account a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his matters?</q> God paſt a Sentence that ſeem'd hard indeed; but this good Man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves it. Here was Contentment unto admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you'll ſay, But Judgment was not executed yet, onely threatned. Right, elſe 'twould have been too late to have enquired how he took the Tydings, when he was not? But the double Aſſurance, that a <hi>Beſom of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> was ready to ſweep him, and by no means to be prevented by him, was enough (to ſpeak as Men) to ſtrike a terrour of Diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on him. But yet when others (who are meer Mortals) might have proved like a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous Sea, we find with him the profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49116:14"/>Calm. Oh! what a Pattern for our Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation?</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>David</hi> is Fourth: And how doth he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit himſelf, when the provoked Majeſty of Heaven ſtrikes even to death that Child he ſo much laboured to preſerve in life? <hi>While it was yet alive</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I faſted and wept: for I ſaid, Who can tell whether God will be gracious to me, that the child may live? But now he is dead, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould I fast? Can I bring him back again? I ſhall go to him, but he ſhall not return to me,</hi> 2 Sam. 12.22, 23. If you reflect upon the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Chapter, and bring down your eyes unto theſe Verſes read, you will find this Judgment on his Child was but on <hi>link</hi> of that long <hi>Chain</hi> prepared for him by the Prophet <hi>Nathan,</hi> from the mouth of God: and when a ſingle link of any Chain is touching of us, it ſhews the reſt are drawing after, and that the whole will quickly reach us. Beſides, this Puniſhment alſo had thoſe Sins that were the <hi>Parents</hi> of it, engraven in ſuch Capital Letters upon its Forehead, that though the Prophet brought him a Pardon ſealed for his own Life, the <hi>way</hi> of bringing him foul Tranſgreſſions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to freſh remembrance, could not but create as freſh, both bluſhings, ſtartlings, and convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in his Conſcience for ſuch great Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages. Moreover, the Child we ſpeak of, was very dear unto him; witneſs his deep Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation on behalf thereof in <hi>Faſting, Prayer,</hi> and <hi>lying on the Earth all night,</hi> Verſe 16, 17.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49116:14"/>in ſpite of the Importunity of his Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors unto the contrary; if poſſible to have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a Reprieve, at leaſt, from Heaven for it. And laſtly, his Servants were afraid to impart the Tydings of the Child's Death to him, for fear he ſhould have done him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Miſchief upon hearing of it: As the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Phraſe importeth<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>; and both the<note n="a" place="margin">Procul dubio ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſibi inferet.</note> 
               <hi>Syriack</hi> and the<note n="b" place="margin">Ne malum ſibi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferat.</note> 
               <hi>Arabick</hi> Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion read.</p>
            <p>Now all theſe Conſiderations put together make it fully manifeſt; that this Stroke of Providence muſt needs fall very heavy; and certainly was enough to ſhake him ſorely; if not link him utterly to the Ground.</p>
            <p>Yet mark his Stilneſs under ſo great a Storm. Whilſt the Child was living, he did his utmoſt to preſerve the Life thereof. But when 'twas Dead, What had he elſe to do; <hi>but at the least to acquieſce in what the Lord had done?</hi> And note, what weighty Arguments he ſtops the mouth of all Impatients by. And they are three,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <q>'Twere moſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable</hi> to Afflict my ſelf (ſaith he) for this Affliction any longer. <hi>Wherefore ſhould I fast: i.</hi> now when the Child is Dead? Produce juſt Cauſe, or any colour of Reaſon for that: if any of you are capable ſo to do. Reaſon is ſo far from Patronizing ſuch a Practice, that it quite abandons it; as carrying,</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49116:15"/>
            <p n="2">2. <q>Perfect <hi>Vanity,</hi> and impertinent <hi>Folly</hi> in the face thereof. <hi>Can I bring him back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? i.</hi> to life. <hi>Kings</hi> can do much, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. And <hi>good Kings,</hi> in all reaſon, ſhould be able to do more than other. (Now in this number <hi>David</hi> was.) But this is above all Mortal Art and Power. The <hi>King of Kings</hi> alone is ſufficient for ſuch Work.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To conclude: <q>I have other buſineſs, and of far greater conſcquence upon my hands, faith tis great Man. Inſtead of fooliſh and fruitleſs afflicting of my thoughts in the bringing of him back; 'tis my grand concernment to bethink me of, and prepare myſelf for,<note n="*" place="margin">Cur immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ferat ab iſſe, quem mox ſubſequeris? <hi>Tert. de Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. c. 9.</hi>
                  </note> going unto him. Whoſe turn is next; God only, and no Mortal, knoweth. But this I know, <hi>that I must go to him;</hi> how ſoon I known not; <hi>He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not return to me.</hi>
               </q> Here lies the Art of putting ſuch an Affair into its right Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. And proves the beſt Improvement of what we may account the worſt of Providences. So ſhall the loſs of ſome <hi>dear Friend</hi> tend to the ſaving of a <hi>dearer ſelf,</hi> our precious Soul.</p>
            <p>This is the Example of that Perſon, who was <hi>A Man after God's own heart;</hi> and who elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where too, and in a worſer Caſe, was yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, <hi>That God ſhould do unto him, as ſeemed good in his eyes,</hi> 2 Sam. 15.26.</p>
            <p>And are not theſe ſuch Steps as are moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be trod in by us?</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49116:15"/>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Job.</hi> Next let us look on <hi>Job:</hi> On him this glorious Character is beſtowed, even by God himſelf, as to a very NONE-SUCH, <hi>viz. A perfect, and an upright man; that feared God, and eſchewed evil,</hi> Chap. 1.8. Nay, his Judge, and the Judge of all the World, declares him innocent, as to a Guilt deſerving ſuch a Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as was falling on him. And, for full proof thereof, makes him a full Amends, and ample Reparation for all him Loſſes, afterwards. Chap. 42.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But that, as yet, could not come under the Sufferer's Cognizance. Well: this ſo excellent a Perſon's Calamities aſſault him like the Billows of the Sea; where furious Tempeſts force them foreward, one upon another's back, till all before them is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwelmed by them. Firſt, the bad News of the <hi>Sabeans</hi> ſeizing on his Oxen and his Aſſes, and ſlaying of his Servants that attended them. Then, how the <hi>Lightning</hi> had conſumed his Sheep and Shepherds all together. Next, that the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> fell upon his Camels, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Keepers too. And laſt of all, (with ſcarcely a time to breathe between them, as we ſay,) the frightful <hi>Death of his Dearest Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> Chap. 1.14, 15, no fewer then ſeven Sons, and three Daughters, by the ſudden fall of an Houſe upon them, is brought unto his Ears. Now, when ſo ſad a Story, with all the frightful Circumſtances of it, ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered ſeriouſly by us, ſhall not we be apt to ſtart theſe queſtion: <hi>What fleſh could bear it:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49116:16"/>what heart of ſteel but must ſink under it?</hi> Well, grant the Caſe be inſupportable unto meer Humanity: yet, <hi>Nothing is too hard for God.</hi> Gen. 18.14. <hi>For tho' the fleſh and the heart doth faile,</hi> where <hi>He is the ſtrength of the heart,</hi> Pſ. 73.26. there is full ſupport notwithſtanding. <hi>His grace s ſufficient,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.9, and can give Conqueſt, and make Triumphant, when the other is utterly overcome and routed. See <hi>here</hi> a Proof! <hi>Job</hi> is affected greatly, and his Soul, affected deeply. <hi>God's hand is very heavy upon him.</hi> But 'tis far from driving him into Rebellion. The moſt humble Submiſſion is practiſed by him: <hi>He worſhiped, and ſaid, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked came I out of my mother's womb, and naked ſhall I return thither. The Lord gave; and the Lord hath taken away: and bleſſed be the name of the Lord,</hi> Job 2.21. Where we ſee plainly; 1. He diſclaims is own right to any Mercies. 2. Proclaims God's ſole Intereſt in them alſo. 3. Thanks him heartily for his <hi>Rod,</hi> as well as for his <hi>Staff.</hi> And what lively Arguments are theſe of a Mind acquieſcing fully in God's good Pleaſure; altho' its one great Pain? Thus 'twas with this good Man: Nay, when the <hi>Hurricane,</hi> that before had overturned his Eſtate, deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Servants, and all his Children, reacheth at laſt his Perſon with a tremendous Judgment; both <hi>an unuſual, and univerſal kind of ſhameful, loathſome, and painful leproſie,</hi> Job 2.7. having great advantage, to his other Afflictions, for forcing him unto Impatience, and Deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49116:16"/>and when <hi>She</hi> that lay in his Boſom (and whoſe Duty 'twas to have adminiſtred Help and Comfort to him, in his Diſtreſs,) inſtead of cooling, labours to inflame the <hi>Feaver</hi> of his Soul, and puts him upon Raving like a <hi>Bedlam,</hi> or a <hi>Devil</hi> rather, Verſe 9. How doth he play the <hi>Man</hi> (ſhall I ſay) yea, with a Vertue more than manly, act the <hi>Saim;</hi> and inſtead of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing overcome, comes off with Victory? Thus, he both, juſtly rebukes his <hi>Wiſe,</hi> and vindicates <hi>God: Thou ſpeakest as one of the fooliſh women ſpeaketh. What? ſhall we receive good at the hand of God, and ſhall we not receive evil,</hi> Verſe 10. <q>
                  <hi>Q. D.</hi> Muſt we be cocker'd ſo, as to have all Days, and no Nights? the Sun ſhine conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but not a Shower, or a Cloud? The Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to laſt all the Year, and Winter never take its turn? moſt fooliſh, fond, and proud Preſumption! That <hi>Man</hi>'s Humour ſhould be ſtill complied with, and the <hi>Supream Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> by no means croſs it! Oh! the vile Abſurdity, the prophane Impudence of the Clay, to preſcribe unto the Potter! Who doth not know (when he remembers, that he is a <hi>Creature</hi>) and will not acknowledge, (if he be a Chriſtian) that we are not to be Carvers for ourſelves, but thankfully ſhould accept the Portion given us? And, in a Journey to the heavenly Kingdom, we ſhould be well content, that foul Ways, ſometimes, as well as fair, ſhould fall unto our ſhare. 'Tis bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, of the worſer kind, to ſtand gently at
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49116:17"/>the <hi>Crib.</hi> but fling and throw at the <hi>Yoke.</hi> Shall God only <hi>ſtroak,</hi> and never <hi>ſtrike</hi> us?</q> Good <hi>Job,</hi> you hear, doth equally acquieſce in <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil,</hi> from the hand of God. <hi>An Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Temper, this!</hi> And it would be our Honour, as 'tis our Duty, to be like him, and make it ours; eſpecially, ſince we live in Goſpel-days, from whence he was as ſo great a diſtance.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Hezekiah.</hi>] But we will proceed to the pious Prince <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> him we ſhall find to be very much of this Celeſtial Grain likewiſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that proportion his Afflictions held with thoſe fore-ſpoken of. 'Tis true, he was a great deal ſhort of moſt of them in the point of <hi>ſuffering,</hi> but little inferiour unto any in that of <hi>Submiſſion.</hi> The Almighty ſends him word, and by a faithful Meſſenger, his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſaiah, That the days ſhould come, that all in his houſe, and what his fathers had laid up in ſtore, ſhould be carried to Babylon, and nothing left.</hi> Moreover, <hi>that the fruit of his loins, his ſons, ſhould be made captives there, and the vilest of them Eunuchs,</hi> Chap. 39.6, 7, 8. Now with this Plundering of his Treaſure, and Enſlaving of his Iſſue, we muſt neceſſarily admit, that a world of other Miſchiefs would be in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, becauſe a vaſt, and forreign, and a barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Army was to do the Execution. And 'tis well known, that ſpoyling the Fruits, burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Houſes, deflouring the Virgins, and murthering the Subjects, with other horrid Villanies, are the Effects of War, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49116:17"/>of bloody Enemies. Now it is plain, that this Divine Threat was pregnant with a numerous train of frightful Evils; altho' any ſingle one of them might have made work e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the beſt of Men to have grappled with. How then doth <hi>Hezekiah</hi> acquit himſelf upon the Tydings? Doth he exclaim of God, and cry out of his unequal Dealing with him? Bad Men will do ſo upon far leſs, and truly none, occaſion; and put the Almighty (in his own Vindication) to make the Blow recoil up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves: <hi>Are not my ways equal? Are not your ways unequal:</hi> Ezek. 18.25, 29. But here was not one word, no, not a thought, to caſt an ill Reflection upon God: You ſhall hear him avow the contrary; and inſtead of an Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of him for the Meſſage, give a ſingular Approbation to it, <hi>Good</hi> (ſaith he to the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, not <hi>bad,</hi>) <hi>is the word of the Lord, which thou hast ſpoken,</hi> Ezek. 39.8. notwithſtanding all the Terrour contained in it. A graceleſs Wretch will be apt to eavil thus: If this be <hi>good,</hi> then what is <hi>bad?</hi> But a godly Soul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth juſtly, that nothing but <hi>good</hi> can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly come from Goodneſs itſelf. And ſuch is God, <hi>being good to all:</hi> but <hi>unto them that love him, making all to work for good.</hi> Thus was this <hi>good King</hi> affected; and we ſhould Copy his Example out unto ourſelves.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Our Bleſſed SAVIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R.</hi>] But what ſhall we ſay to our <hi>Bleſſed Lord?</hi> He cometh next to be conſidered, according to that Order we
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49116:18"/>have purſued hitherto, and at the firſt propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. If the <hi>Members</hi> have done excellently, the <hi>Head</hi> will certainly ſurpaſs them all! He taught, and liv'd this heavenly Leſſon of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> and <hi>Submiſſion</hi> unto GOD, in his whole courſe on Earth. It were beſide my Purpoſe, to inſiſt Diſtreſſes, <hi>To poſſeſs our ſouls in pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> Luke 21.19. And for his Practice, there is no occaſion to be large on that, neither: 'tis ſo well known to every Perſon that is but or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily verſed in the Holy Goſpel. His Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, out of all doubt, conſidered with all the Circumſtances appertaining thereunto, are not to be paralell'd by any Inſtance that the Earth could ever afford. When we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how <hi>great</hi> and <hi>good</hi> he was; what meaſure, tho', was meeted out unto him, and with what Contentment all that was <hi>bad,</hi> and the very <hi>worst,</hi> was put up by him; it muſt amaze us! He was the GOD, that made, preſerved, and rules the World; and will moſt certainly be its Judge at laſt. He took our Nature, and came among us; not to condemn us, or accuſe us, or to do any hurt at all unto us; but the greateſt good, (tho' we deſerv'd worſt Uſage at his hands,) <hi>viz.</hi> to be <hi>the Author of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Salvation to us.</hi> Yet was he undervalu'd, reviled, and abuſed, at as bad a rate as it was poſſible for the ſpite of Earth and Hell to do it: He is ſeized on as a <hi>Malefactor,</hi> when moſt innocent, and the greateſt <hi>Benefactor</hi> the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49116:18"/>World ever had; impriſoned, ſpit on, buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetted, ſcourged, and crucified, as one of the worſt and vileſt of Offenders. But with what a calm and quiet Spirit doth he take it all? The Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> foretold his meek and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Temper long before his Incarnation, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>He was oppreſſed, and afflicted, yet he opened not his mouth: He is brought as a lamb to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and as a ſheep before his ſhearer is dumb, ſo he opened not his mouth,</hi> Eſ. 53.7. We all know the quietneſs of thoſe harmleſs, and moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Creatures, under the Butcher's hand and knife. Alas! with how much eaſe could the Lord Jeſus have frown'd his Enemies Bodies to the Grave, and their Souls to Hell: or Both at once unto the place of everlaſting Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? And it had been ſurely done; but that his Lamb-like Soul abhorr'd, <hi>Vile Mortals ſweet revenge.</hi> He alſo knew it was his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Will, that <hi>the Just ſhould ſuffer for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njust,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.18; and <hi>from</hi> them too: and unto him he thus ſubmits himſelf: <hi>Not my Will, but thine be done,</hi> Luke 22.42. He will not chuſe for himſelf: but takes with great content, what God is pleas'd to carve unto him. Nay, when his ſervant <hi>Peter</hi> would by a valiant and a righteous Force have reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him; he bids him hold his hand; and for this reaſon; It was his Father's pleaſure, that he ſhould thus ſuffer, and he ought not hinder his moſt ready compliance with it: <hi>The Cup which my Father hath given me, ſhall I not drink
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49116:19"/>it?</hi> John 18.11. Thus hath our Saviour walk'd before us, breaking the Ice, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Way unto us; that we, with leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret, and greater eaſe might go after him. This is St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s obſervation: <hi>Christ ſuffered for us, leaving us an example, that we ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his ſteps. Who, when he was reviled, reviled not again; when he ſuffered, threatned not: but comitted himſelf to him that judgeth righteouſly,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.21, 23. And if <hi>we abide in Christ;</hi> in this his <hi>Patience,</hi> as well as other Vertues, <hi>we ought to walk, as he walked,</hi> 1 John 2.6.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Paul.</hi> To conclude <hi>Examples:</hi> The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was an ingenious Scholar, and very apt Diſciple to his moſt excellent Maſter and Inſtructer, the ever Bleſſed Jeſus. Pray mark how he had conn'd his Leſſon, and got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it perſectly by heart too, by his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſion: <hi>I have</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">'Tis a work of Learning, and Exerciſe, and Care. <hi>S. Chryſ. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>learned</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in whatſoever eſtate I am, therewith to be contented,</hi> Phil. 4.11. In Health, and Plenty; in Peace and Liberty, this is no difficult Leſſon, all Men know. But in the caſe of Sickneſs, Poverty; loſs of Friends, Eſtate, of Liberty; or in the danger of Life: how many then will quickly cry out, <hi>This is an hard ſaying: who can bear it?</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer them: <hi>Such a one as</hi> Paul <hi>can do it.</hi> And further; he that <hi>hath been taught of God, and hath learned the truth, as it is in Jeſus:</hi> even He can do it alſo. If all the World ſhould frown
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49116:19"/>upon them; if Midnight-Darkneſs hide all Comforts from them; if neither <hi>Sun, nor Moon, nor Stars appear</hi> unto them; yet theſe People are able to retire within themſelves; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>run into the Name of the Lord;</hi> and All is well. For <hi>the Name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower; the righteous runneth into it, and is ſafe;</hi> ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> Prov. 18.10. This alſo made the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtle ſay; <hi>He could do all things, through Christ that ſtrengthen'd him,</hi> Phil. 4.13. And the Context ſheweth, that this <hi>Doing</hi> Chiefly reſpecteth <hi>Suffering.</hi> Wherein Chriſt's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with the Soul converts Complaints into Thankſgivings, and Repinings to Rejoycings. The Church of old makes a clear Proof of this: <hi>Altho the Fig-tree ſhall not bloſſom, neither ſhall fruit be in the Vine; the labour of the Olive ſhall fail, and the Field ſhall yield no meat; the Flock ſhall be cut off from the Fold, and there ſhall be no Herd in the Stall: Yet I will Rejoyce in the Lord, I will joy in the God of my Salvation,</hi> Habak. 13, 18. And how are Murmuring, and Impatience ſent into Exile then; never to take harbour in ſuch Breaſts, as theſe? Well, now we know, how quiet, and at what hearts eaſe, the holy Apoſtle was in in the worſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. <hi>He was content!</hi> And what are Any, or the very Beſt of us, that in our Sufferings we ſhould not bring our Minds to that Sedate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, wherein his was, who was ſo much <hi>Above us?</hi> The plain reaſon is: Becauſe, in Grace, we are ſo much <hi>Beneath him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49116:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Recapitulation.</hi>] Now, looking back upon this Cloud of Witneſſes, we muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; that they all conſpire to ring it loudy in our ears: <hi>Let Patience have its perfect Work</hi> within you, whatever Diſtreſſes lye upon you. If we are Real Chriſtians, to be Meek with <hi>Moſes;</hi> to hold our Peace with <hi>Aaron;</hi> leave God to himſelf with <hi>Eli;</hi> poſſeſs our thoughts with our own approaching End, as <hi>David</hi> did; to bleſs God's Name for our Adverſity, as well for Proſperity, after <hi>Job</hi>'s example; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove his Methods, altho ſevere, in a compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with <hi>Hezekiah;</hi> ſubmit our Wills entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto his; as was <hi>our Saviour</hi>'s holy Practice: and laſtly, to learn with the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles; <hi>in all eſtates to be contented.</hi> If God ſee meet to take away Eſtate, to be content; if Name, content; if Health, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; if Liberty, Friends, or Children, nay, Father, Husband, or Wife, dear to us as our ſelves; yea, or life it ſelf; <hi>to be Contented ſtill.</hi> Whatever Diſtreſs the gracious Providence ſhall bring us to, it is our Duty, after the Examples of all theſe Famous Worthies (Chriſt Jeſus Soldiers) and the Captain of their and our Salvation himſelf; to learn the Doctrine of my Text: <hi>To be dumb, and open not our mouth; and that, becauſe God doth it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo much of the Examples.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49116:20"/>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Arguments.</hi>] Now for <hi>Powerful Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> which will evince the neceſſary Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that Pious People do lye under, to bear Afflictions without Impatience, and a Quiet Mind. There are but five I ſhall make uſe of: but that which bringeth up the Rear, if I may not ſay, 'twill prove a <hi>Mother of Nations;</hi> at leaſt, 'twill ſhew, it hath a Teeming Womb, and bring us forth a double Number to the whole Tale mention'd.</p>
            <p>They are theſe in brief: 1. Hereby they are conformed to the Beſt of Saints, and in their Beſt Condition, on the Earth. 2. The firſt and ſecond Birth do <hi>Both</hi> diſpoſe to Troubles. 3. Impatience is ſo far from helping then, that it doth more hurt. 4. There is Undoubted Good unto the Godly at the Bottom of all they ſuffer. And 5ly; <hi>'Tis the Lord that ſendeth their Diſtreſſes to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. Good Chriſtians ſhould bear with Patience their Diſtreſſes; becauſe <hi>They but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them to the best of Saints, and in their Best Condition upon Earth.</hi> Then why ſuch ſore Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints among them? Had there been <hi>formerly</hi> no famous Inſtances given to this Purpoſe; who, that hath only taſted Holy Scriptures can be ignorant; that<note n="*" place="margin">In origine ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim mundi Abel a fratre occidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Jacob fuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Joſeph ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nundatur, &amp; David Saul perſequitur, <hi>&amp;c. S. Cypr. de Exhort. Mort. cap. 11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> had <hi>Generally</hi> this Meaſure meted out
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49116:21"/>unto them; nay, <hi>preſſed down, ſhaken together, and running over;</hi> eſpecially to the <hi>Last;</hi> and I may ſay, the <hi>Best</hi> of them, our Lord's moſt dear Diſciples? 'Tis certain that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; not barely, that <hi>They were appointed to aſſlictions,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.3; but that he thought, <hi>God had ſet Them forth as Men appointed to death it ſelf: for they were made,</hi> in their Sufferings, <hi>a Spectacle to the World</hi> (the upper and the lower) <hi>of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and Men too,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.9. And ſhould it now be accounted a grievous matter for the Succeſſors to be like their Predeceſſors? What? Are we better than they? Alas! How much beneath them? Whoſe Modeſty will not prompt him freely to confeſs himſelf far ſhorter of them in real worth, than he is in time behind them? And, pray now; do we not all deſire to be Partakers with them, in point of Proſit; and ſhall we grudge our ſhare of Pains? Would we arrive at the bleſſed Harbour where they are driving an heavenly Trade; and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to croſs the ſwelling Waves after them? Is it fit and equal, that we ſhould ſettle in their <hi>Canaan,</hi> without the Troubles and the Dangers of that <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> which they have paſs'd, and is the ſtrait way to it? If we have hopes to be ſuch as They in Heaven, it muſt not be grudg'd, if we be like them on the Earth. How proper is it, that a Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ſhould be betwixt the <hi>Eellow-members?</hi> And how much more, with the <hi>Head</hi> it ſelf? Is it not written, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.10. <hi>That the Captain
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49116:21"/>of our ſalvation was made perfect thro' ſufferings?</hi> He put not on his <hi>Crown,</hi> but going from the <hi>Croſs:</hi> nor ſat he on the <hi>Throne,</hi> before he had hung upon the <hi>Tree.</hi> And ſhall it be thought intollerable, or any thing hard; to follow <hi>ſuch a Leader? And unto ſuch a Journey's End?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, as I ſaid before, Saints ſuffering State was <hi>best</hi> unto them: even ſo it is. The <hi>Riddle</hi> was of old; that the <hi>Eater affords meat, and the ſtrong ſweetneſs.</hi> Judg. 14.14. And truly, good Men's <hi>ſorrows</hi> on Earth bring <hi>ſolace</hi> down from Heaven unto them. When the Knife was putting to <hi>Iſaac's</hi> Throat by the ſad Father; an Angel comes and puts a Ram into his room, unto his greater joy, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.14. <hi>As a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pittieth his children; ſo the Lord doth them that fear him. For he knoweth our frame; he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth that we are but dust.</hi> Parents are wont to be moſt tender to their weak, and ſickly Ones: others can make a better ſhift. And ſhall not he that puts theſe Bowels into them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards theirs, have them much more within himſelf to His? What tho' a Mother <hi>Should forget her ſucking babe;</hi> Eſa. 49.15. (and ſuch, a Worſe-thing-than-a-Brute, is found ſometimes in Humane ſhape) <hi>God will not, cannot do</hi> ſo. We read, that ſuffering Saints are ſaid to <hi>Glory in tribulations.</hi> And <hi>Glorying is</hi> no ſign of <hi>Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> and <hi>Repining.</hi> How ſhould impatient La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations be able then to keep their Ground; <hi>When light afflictions, and for a moment, work a far more exceeding and external weight of glory?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49116:22"/>
            <p>This is the 1ſt Argument. And the 2d will prove like unto it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. Diſtreſſes ſhould not raiſe great Storms, and Tempeſts in the pious Soul; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our <hi>First, and ſecond Birth do, both, diſpoſe us to them.</hi> As we are <hi>Men,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> they are the Lot appointed for us. And ought we not; and <hi>therefore,</hi> to be quiet under them? How great's the Folly; to be ſo diſturbed, at what is not to be avoided? <hi>Man,</hi> now, <hi>is born to trouble, as the ſparks fly upward;</hi> as we heard, <hi>at first,</hi> was ſpoken by Holy <hi>Job.</hi> And all Men know; neither Art, nor Force can make the Flames deſcend; but they are always mounting upward. That is the Nature of them. Wherefore to be Impatient under Trouble is to be quarreling with the Almighty Majeſty, by whom a Humane Body and a Rational Soul is beſtowed on us. And ſo there is Ingratitude, and Rebellion link'd together. Thus to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite him, that brought them out of nothing by meer Bounty; and by the ſame, hath made them capable of injoying all things, and the beſt of all; <hi>His bleſſed ſelf for ever:</hi> if they will be ruled by him.</p>
            <p>And for the <hi>ſecond Birth:</hi> it commonly hath the throws, and pangs of a travelling Woman: and, often, worſer far. General Experience makes a proof of this. However, in growing up unto Maturity there is no eſcaping of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity: <hi>Through much tribulation</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul) we must enter the kingdom of God. We must:</hi> 'tis
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49116:22"/>neceſſarily, and unavoidably ſo. Heaven is on high: and it is hard to climb an Hill; a ſteep, and long one, eſpecially. The Lungs will la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; Feet will faulter; and Bones will ake, in doing it. Were there no Difficulty in our way to Glory, and we met no Troubles in our Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel thither, we might indeed be <hi>called,</hi> and <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted</hi> Chriſtians: but how we ſhould be really ſo; I mean, <hi>Legitimate Children</hi> unto God, is hard to manifeſt, and may very well be doubted, from the holy Apoſtle's words, who ſaith; <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5, 6, 7, &amp;c. <hi>My ſon, deſpiſe not thou the chaſtening of the Lord, nor faint when thou art rebuked of him. For whom the Lord loveth he chaſtneth; and ſcourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every ſon whom he receiveth: If ye endure cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening, God dealeth with you as with ſons; for what ſon is he whom his father chaſtneth not? But if ye are</hi> without chaſtiſement, <hi>whereof</hi> all <hi>are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, then are you</hi> baſtards, <hi>and not ſons.</hi> Let now a diſtreſſed Chriſtian ſeriouſly ponder this; and let him <hi>not ſtagger through <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief;</hi> and 'tis not poſſible for Diſcontent to keep its poſt any longer in his Heart. Let him be <hi>ſtrong in Faith,</hi> and this will turn his Croſſes into Crowns; and make what's bitter to the outward, reliſh ſweetly to the inward Man. Now if ever, the Apoſtle's words will be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly verified with the upright, tho' afflicted, Perſon: <hi>We faint not, but tho' our outward man</hi> ſhould <hi>periſh, yet the inward man is renewed day by day,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.16. <hi>Earth's Darlings,</hi> and who have <hi>their portion only in this life,</hi> cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49116:23"/>a world of Miſeries: and ſhall <hi>Heaven's Off-ſpring</hi> be diſorder'd at abiding what both Grace and Nature hath prepared for them? Eſpecially, ſince Truth it ſelf hath plainly told them, That their Affliction is but a certain Token of God's Affection.</p>
            <p>Now, ſurely; there is no reaſon for <hi>Repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> but occaſion rather of <hi>Rejoycing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. <hi>Impatience is ſo far from doing ſervice to us in our Sufferings, that it makes our Caſe a great deal worſer than it was before; and bringeth many, and very evil Inconveniences with it.</hi> Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that under a ſore Diſtreſs we ſhould make hoarſe our throat with crys,<note place="margin">Impatientes non efficiunt ut a malis eruantur; ſed ut mala gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior a patiantur. <hi>S. Aug. de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient. cap. 2.</hi>
               </note> and drown our bed with tears, and crack our brain with cares, and break our heart with ſighs and groans: what would the Upſhot be of all this pitiful Paſſion? Would ſuch a Courſe, ſo void of Reaſon and Religion, prove an effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Relief unto us? Would the loſs of Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood be hereby repaired? A bodily Sickneſs be recovered? The Life of a deceaſed Friend again reſtored? Or any Calamity, whatever, be removed; or ſo much as eaſed? Alas! poor ſilly Creatures as we are! what do we elſe by ſuch a Procedure, but plainly imitate the folly of the <hi>Fly,</hi> when 'tis intangled in the Spider's Web: She makes a Noiſe, and is greatly Fluttering; and hampers herſelf <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> the faſter in that Net; and becomes a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49116:23"/>ſooner Prey to him that ſpread it. Methinks we are reſembled fitly by the corded Beaſt whoſe head the Axe, and heart the Butcher's Knife hath ſtruck; which, the more it ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, <hi>ſilly Wretch,</hi> the faſter letteth out its lood, and life therewith together. Such is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Iſſue of Mens Impatience: <hi>They look for peace, and there is no good; for a time of healing, and behold trouble.</hi> The Benefit, which they promiſe, proves a Dammage to them. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, a manifold Miſchief flows from hence, How can the Offices of Love and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice be diſcharged, as they ought to be, unto Relations, by a Mind diſordered, and unhing'd by this Diſtemper? Expect, as ſoon, a Man that hath a Palſie, or is Bedrid, ſhould fetch you Food, or make your Fire. Beſide, it ſo affects the <hi>Body,</hi> that ſometimes Death itſelf is quickly call'd unto it: always the Seeds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in lingring Sickneſſes, are deeply rooted in it. And how untuned the <hi>Soul</hi> muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be, and bar'd its acting with ſpiritual life, and vigour, is very eaſily underſtood: The griefs, and cares, and fears are apt to uſher in Deſpair; but certainly drive out Faith, and Hope, and Love. To conclude, he that is thus captivated, cannot be capable to pay due Homage to his God. How ſhould he, as becomes him, fear his <hi>Threats,</hi> obey his <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts,</hi> truſt in his <hi>Promiſes,</hi> and rejoyce before him with <hi>Thankſgiving?</hi> I will ſay but this: Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, and Murmuring under the Hand of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49116:24"/>God is a great Affront unto his bleſſed Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty; and cannot be well taken by him. Nay, he hath often ſet the Marks of his Diſpleaſure on it. I will paſs by that which<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 16, 7, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Numb. 14.27, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> once and again hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded thereof: remembring you only of the Apoſtle's Caution to the <hi>Corinthians, Neither murmur ye, as ſome of them alſo murmured, and were deſtroyed of the deſtroyer,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.10. We may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude of this (wherewith I cloſe the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment): If we belong to God, and are diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied at his Dealings with us, we lay a kind of force upon him: <hi>Either to keep us longer in his Furnace, or to remove us thence with our Droſs upon us.</hi> And ſurely the Choice is not the beſt, on either ſide. Wherefore we muſt rebuke Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience: and the rather, for that—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. There is undoubted Good at the bottom of all Afflictions to the truly Godly. Then, what pretence for Diſcontentment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them? Had they their riſe from an Heart replete with Vengeance, Rage, and Fury to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us; and were they the Blows of a bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Enemy, that aim'd at nothing leſs than our utter ruine; our Caſe were then ſo ſad, that 'twould be hard to find out Comfort for us; and ſeem unequal, to condemn a turbulent Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in Diſtreſſes. But, bleſſed be GOD, things go at quite another rate: The Cloud that is <hi>Darkneſs unto Egypt, is Light to Iſrael,</hi> Exod. 14.20. The Devil and his Angels, who
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49116:24"/>may be Executioners to the righteous and good Providence in our Sufferings, are none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than moſt malignantly diſaffected to God's People. Yet, how bloodily ſoever they are bent; and whatſoever Miſchief they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to effect: that which happens, is not what their Malice doth deſign, but what God's Mercy doth direct. The Axe never heweth; but when, and as, the Carpenter ſtrikes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. And the ſharpeſt Sword will fetch no Blood, but from the Hand that wields, and ſmiteth with it. But Men, and evil Spirits too, are <hi>Tools,</hi> which God, (as far as it is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to him) maketh uſe of: And he lays them by again, as he thinks good; and <hi>then</hi> they muſt be quiet in ſpite of all their Cruelty. The Condition of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 1, &amp; 2. Pſ. 17.13, 14. Eſ. 10.5, 6, 7, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Job</hi> doth make this evident. And both the Pſalmiſt, and the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> plainly declare as much. So that who, or whatever brings a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity to us; we muſt conclude, 'tis ſent of God for good. And, if we wiſely attend our Duty, 'twill be with us, as with<note n="‖" place="margin">He in his Excile li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in greater ſtate than his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try could afford; ſaid to his Servants, <hi>Sirs, We had been <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndone, if we had not been <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done.</hi> Plut. Them.</note> 
               <hi>Themiſtocles, Better in our trouble, than without it.</hi> This is not peradventure, preſently, perceived by us, in every Tryal. Nor do the Sick, or Wounded, at the firſt or ſecond, or (may be) many applications of the moſt proper and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49116:25"/>ſoveraign Medecines to them, forthwith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Cure, or find Eaſe thereon. Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, 'tis better with them; becauſe they are in the ready way thereto. And is it not egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Folly to exclaim againſt, or have hard thoughts of, either Doctor or Surgeon, for a griping Belly, or a ſmarting Leg, when 'tis to ſave the Life, and to recover Health? Should Sufferers be ſo far from benefit in their Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, that they do not yet ſo much as under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the meaning of them: why, they ſhould know that the Golden Oar is cover'd with coarſer Earth; and it will ask both pains and patience to dig deep enough to reach it. And our bleſſed Saviour's words to his Servant <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> are very applicable here: <hi>What I do, thou knowest not yet; but ſhalt know hereafter,</hi> Joh. 13.7. Wait then with quietneſs; and thou wilt ſooner find the Treaſure. But if thou quarrel with thy Medicines, and ſtorm at him that doth apply them, it muſt be longer, if e'er, thou get a Cure; when a ſubmiſſive Spirit will ſoon be healed. God muſt be met, in his own way. As he<note n="‖" place="margin">1 Kings 19.11.</note> comes not in a <hi>great ſtrong Wind; nor in the</hi> frightful <hi>Earthquake; nor in the</hi> furious <hi>Fire: but in the ſtill ſmall Voice:</hi> we muſt attend him alſo with a ſtill and quiet Spirit. Turbulent Paſſions in the Soul, are like loud Noiſes, and deafning Clamours at the Ears. Theſe marr the Hearing, and ſo the Underſtanding. Hence 'tis, that in ſuch a <hi>Lurry</hi> we cannot <hi>hear the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49116:25"/>Rod, and who hath appointed it,</hi> Mic. 6.9; ſo as to underſtand, and receive, the good God means us by it. Yet good is ſurely meant thereby. What prudent Father ever did cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his Child, but for his benefit? And how ſhould Infinite Wiſdom, with equal Love, have any other Aim? Afflictions are God's <hi>File,</hi> to rub off the ruſt of Sin that it may not rot our Souls. His <hi>Fan,</hi> to ſcatter far away the Duſt and Chaff, which are apt to bury our Grain in Uſeleſneſs. Yea, and his <hi>Furnace</hi> too, where the Droſs and Tin is ſever'd, that the Mettal may be pure and bright. Are not all theſe for greateſt good? But the Apoſtle is expreſs, in ſaying, That tho' ſome <hi>men correct for pleaſure; God chaſtens us for our profit,</hi> Heb. 12.10. And the Pſalmiſt had the proof upon himſelf, for he profeſſeth, Pſal. 119.71. <hi>'Twas good for him that he was afflicted.</hi> For <hi>he was gone aſtray be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that met him, and brought him back to God.</hi> And how far he might have wander'd, to the utter loſing of his Way; had not his wild Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer been ſtopt by the Rod of God, who can tell? Certain 'tis, that long Proſperity is a Bait to all Impiety; and no Affliction oft-times proves the very worſt Affliction: Yea, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity the greateſt Puniſhment. Therefore God threatned, in his high Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpleaſure,<note place="margin">Hoſea 4.14. Eſay 1.5. Hoſea 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>Not to puniſh the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, nor the wives in Iſrael for their whoredoms; to ſtrike Judah no more:</hi> and <hi>let Ephraim alone in his idolatry.</hi> When
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49116:26"/>Providence ſmiting of a Pious Man with Lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs onely, preventing his running away from God: or with Bodily Sickneſs, 'tis for preſerving his Soul in, or recovering it to, Health. Such Mens Loſſes of Temporal Riches, are for ſecuring Eternal to them: and Death's removal of their Earthly Friends, is for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing, and faſter ſetling their Friendſhip with the Heavenly Majeſty. Nay, and their own approaching End ſerves for preparing them unto an Endleſs Bliſs.</p>
            <p>And where's the Cauſe now of Complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? How great's the reaſon, rather, of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing: at leaſt, of Silence, and Submiſſion? Eſpecially, when the 5th and laſt Argument ſhall be conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. <hi>Thou, Lord, didst it.</hi> And this is what the Royal Pſalmiſt urgeth in my Text. Which only (tho our Proverb aptly ſaith, <hi>Store's no Sore</hi>) in mine opinion, might be ſufficient to give repoſe and quiet to a ſincere Chriſtian in his greateſt troubles; ſuppoſe it be conſidered in its juſt extent. Should I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it like the <hi>Tower of</hi> David, <hi>builded for an Armory, wherein there hung a thouſand Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, all Shields of mighty Men;</hi> it were not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken much amiſs. I'm ſure 'tis no Hyperbole, inſtead of calling it a ſingle Argument, to ſay an Heap of thoſe are lodg'd therein. For with a little Patience you ſhall ſee it bringing forth at leaſt One Decade of them. Only 'tis requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, that we ſhould retrieve our former
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49116:26"/>thoughts upon the words, and with this ſhort Improvement. <hi>Thou, Lord, didst it;</hi> ſeemeth to make the holy Prophet after this manner to addreſs himſelf to God: <q>
                  <hi>O Lord, I ſtill'd my Soul, and ſtopt my Mouth under my doleful Caſe; becauſe no Luck, or Chance without me, none Evil Accident on me, none Inadvertency or Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in me; no Luſts of Men, or Rage of Devils against me, was the Prime Cauſe of my Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Whatſoever Miſchief mine Enemies, or my ſinful Self, might be inſtrumental in unto me; 'twas only as thy Juſtice, and thy Goodneſs gave Commiſſion, or Permiſſion thereunto. Whence, mine Impatience were nothing elſe but Quarelling at thy Providence.</hi>
               </q> Therefore was I ſilent, both as to Words and Thoughts too: Becauſe <hi>Thou, Lord, didst it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Now the Firſt-Born of this Argument ſhews it thus: <hi>Thou, Lord, didst it:</hi> Thou, whoſe we are, All, and Every of us: the very Work of thine own Hands. <hi>We are the Clay, and thou our Potter,</hi> Eſay 64.8. And who can juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take offence at thee,<note place="margin">Ye are not your own, <hi>1 Cor. 6.19.</hi> We are the Lords, <hi>Rom. 14.8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for doing as thou pleaſest with thine own?</hi> Mat. 20.15. If the Potter make one Veſſel of ſiner Earth than he doth another: and appointeth <hi>this</hi> for the common ſervice of the Kitchin, when <hi>that</hi> is to be ſet up in the Cloſet; where is the reaſon to complain? Nay, if one, or more, or many of them be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into Potſherds by him; is he not without
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49116:27"/>controul; for that? Altho <hi>Himſelf</hi> be not; yet <hi>They</hi> are his own, But we are <hi>much more</hi> God's: to be dealt with by him, as it ſeemeth good unto him. So, if the Husbandman will put one Parcel of his Sheep into rich Paſtures, when the reſt can hardly live upon the barren Common: and fatten ſome of his working Cattel with Food and Reſt, for Weeks and Months together; whilſt conſtant Labour and coarſer Provender make others leaner than a Rake (as we ſay): who ſhall call him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for this? Are they not his own? But we have no ſuch property in what is called <hi>Ours:</hi> as the Almighty hath in <hi>us.</hi> In truth, we are but <hi>Stewards:</hi> He <hi>Abſolute Lord.</hi> We are, All; the Higheſt in the World, reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible unto God: but God to None. Then at what rate ſoever it pleaſeth him to deal with us; tho he afflict us ſorely in our Perſon, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, or Eſtate; our Duty is to ſay, <hi>We muſt be dumb, becauſe thou, Lord, didst it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Thou, Lord, didst it.</hi> Who canſt do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou wilt do; and none can hinder thee. Thy whole pleaſure ſhall be effected <hi>in Heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen. 18.14.</hi> Is any thing too hard for God?</note> 
               <hi>and Earth, the Seas, and all deep places; nor is there any thing too hard for thee,</hi> Pſal. 135.6. And, Lord, if thou ſendeſt one Affliction on me; it might have been an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. Haſt thou withdrawn one choiceſt Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; why is there any left? Say, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of our Life were gone: why hath not our
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49116:27"/>Life it ſelf taken wing, and flown away toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with it? Should we ſay, <hi>Nay;</hi> would that have prevented it? Or was there Power e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, or Craft at leaſt, with us, to have put a Bar to? Who is ſo great a Fool, as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain ſuch Thoughts? Let God once ſpeak the word; 'tis inſtantly done, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 12.25. If he command Eſtate, or Health, or Liberty, or Friends away; if he <hi>require our Soul:</hi> can we compel, perſwade, or intreat the longer ſtay of any of them? Admit it then, that it may go hard with us in <hi>ſome</hi> reſpects: why is it better; wherefore not bad, or at the very worſt, in <hi>all?</hi> He that hath only given a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle laſh upon our Hand, could have cut off our Head; or ſtabb'd us at the Heart; if that had been his mind. How eaſie were it for Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Power ſo to do? And is not God thus fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed? Wherefore, well might the holy Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſay in his diſtreſs, and the very beſt of us ſay after him upon the like occaſion; <hi>I was dumb, I open'd not my mouth; becauſe thou, Lord, didst it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Thou, Lord, didst it.</hi> Thou haſt ſeen it meet to take (ſuppoſe) One Mercy from us: but yet haſt left us Many: Nay, haſt beſtowed Hundreds, Thouſands on us! For <hi>thy compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions never fail; but are new every morning,</hi> Lam. 3.23. And <hi>thou dost Encompaſs them, that truly trust in thee, with mercy,</hi> Pſal. 32.10. When we, with grief <hi>remember,</hi> what a Bleſſing we have loſt; ſhall we <hi>forget</hi> the while thoſe many
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49116:28"/>others which we ſtill injoy? What Favours, much above all reckoning, doſt thou, O Lord, afford, for Soul and Body too? Unto our ſelves and Friends likewiſe? If we be real Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, we then muſt be Diſciples to the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt; and ſay our Leſſon that he teacheth; <hi>How precious are thy thoughts unto me, O God? How great is the ſum of them? If I ſhould count them, they are more in number than the ſand,</hi> Pſal. 139.17, 18. That only one, which is worth ten thouſand others; the Gift of thy bleſſed Son, <hi>to die for our offences, riſe for our juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and at thy right-hand to live, for making interceſſion for us;</hi> that we may have Pardon, Pity; Support and Comfort under all our Preſſures; What an Invaluable Mercy is it! We have God's ſure Promiſe, That <hi>he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leave, nor forſake his People,</hi> Heb. 13.5. till he hath brought them through the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of this World in ſafety to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Canaan.</hi> God gave his Son unto this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry purpoſe. And as <hi>Joſhua,</hi> who was the Type of Jeſus, led the Carnal <hi>Iſrael</hi> into the Promiſed Land <hi>Below;</hi> ſo <hi>Jeſus,</hi> by him typified, will certainly conduct the Spiritual <hi>Iſrael</hi> into that <hi>Above.</hi> Oh, Raviſhing Bleſſing! And the very Quinteſſence of all Bleſſings! Able to make a Pious Soul <hi>Rejoyce</hi> in ſpite of Sorrow; and to triumph in its Tribulations. To be ſure; it will, and muſt have influence on him in his Sufferings, to ſay with <hi>David; Lord, I am dumb: becauſe thou didst it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:49116:28"/>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Thou, Lord, didſt it.</hi> Who, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, haſt made it better with us; much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than with many others, much our betters. Imagine ſome of us have loſt a fair Eſtate: there are thoſe good People who, with their Eſtate, have loſt their Health too. Say, thou art ſick: why ſuch a Friend, or Neighbour, or Acquaintance at the leaſt, is ſick and lame withal: and ſome (poor Souls) with Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty into the bargain. Admit, that thou haſt parted with One dear Relation: Many are they, that have loſt Many ſuch; and ſome All. If Death hath ſnatch'd away one Child from thee: there are thoſe that have none left them now, tho time was, they had many. Hath the Juſt Providence removed an Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate Mother from thee? There are not a few whom it hath bereaved of ſuch a Father. And ſeveral that it hath made Orphans; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute both of Father, and of Mother too. If a Good Man's <hi>Help-meet</hi> be gone: there are Pious Women that have had their <hi>Head</hi> taken from them. Whoever thou art that truly feareſt God, and art too much complaining of thy Infelicity, be but perſwaded to leave off poring only on thy ſelf, and look abroad a little; and thou ſhalt find, Thou haſt the <hi>light ſide of the Cloud,</hi> when many others muſt be contented <hi>with the dark.</hi> Remember that moſt excellent Perſon, who ſtandeth upon Scripture-Record with this moſt ſad Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of his to God, <hi>Lover, and friend hast
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49116:29"/>thou put far from me, and mine acquaintance into darkneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">—Similes alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum reſpice Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Mitius iſta feres. <hi>Ovid. Met 15.8.</hi>
               </note> Pſal. 88.18: and ſurely then upon the whole, thou muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that thou oughteſt to ſay; I will ſay nothing: <hi>becauſe thou, Lord, didst it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Thou, Lord, didst it.</hi> Thou, who art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly able to ſupply my greateſt Wants; ſupport me under my heavieſt Loads; repair me for my greateſt Loſſes. <hi>Is any thing too hard for God, with whom all things are poſſible,</hi> Gen. 18.14. Matth. 19.26. I grant; were any one's Neceſſities unrelievable; his Burdens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable; or his Damages irrepairable; the Caſe of ſuch a Perſon were very lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table! But good and wiſe Chriſtians do <hi>All</hi> know better things. And to the Upright Man; that God, who is his <hi>Conſtant Hope,</hi> both <hi>Can,</hi> and <hi>Will,</hi> moſt certaily prove his <hi>Effectual Help.</hi> Is it not promiſed; <hi>My God ſhall ſupply all your Need according to his Riches?</hi> Phil. 4.19. And we are aſſured of his <hi>Sufficiency</hi> in the laſt words, as of his <hi>Good-will</hi> in thoſe foregoing. And how punctually was it made good to holy <hi>Job</hi> after all his long and diſmal Sufferings: <hi>when his latter end was better than his beginning?</hi> Job 42.12. All was made good <hi>in kind</hi> to him, that had before been taken from him. And the <hi>Lord's Hand is not ſhortned now,</hi> nor <hi>his Heart hardned,</hi> neither: but, if that be beſt, he can, and will do ſo again, to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49116:29"/>ſuffering Saints of the preſent Age alſo. Had <hi>Job</hi>'s Condition never to have been match'd in future Times, wherefore ſhould the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>James, Jam.</hi> 5.11. direct our eyes point blank on this Example for our encouragement in Afflictions? But ſo, you know, he doth. However, God will never fail to make up e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Loſs unto his faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,<note place="margin">Pſalm 73.26. Lamen. 3.24. 2 Cor. 12.9.</note> 
               <hi>in value,</hi> where 'tis not ſit it ſhould be done <hi>in kind.</hi> Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if all be gone beſides, will be, and is his People's <hi>Portion.</hi> And is not this enough, and infinitely the better Share! Who that's afflicted but muſt ſay: <hi>I am dumb;</hi> becauſe <hi>thou, Lord, didst it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Thou, Lord, didst it.</hi> Thou took'ſt away my deareſt Relations (whether Husband, Wife, Father, Mother, Child, or Friend) whom (bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be thy Name) thou tookeſt into Covenant with thyſelf before. (And for this once, I will be limitted thus.) I am bereaved, Lord; and 'tis thy righteous doing too. But oh! what better proviſion haſt thou made for him, or them, than I could ever poſſibly do, had they ſtaid with me? Mine is the <hi>loſs,</hi> 'tis true; but theirs the <hi>infinite gain!</hi> For, what is Earth to Heaven! What is a Husband, Wife; a Father, Mother; a Child, or Friend, to God?<note place="margin">Cum chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quos diligimus de ſeculo exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, gandendum</note> Now we are ſure, that thoſe, who live a while <hi>to Him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> ſhall live <hi>with Him above</hi> for <hi>potius quam dolendwn.</hi> S. Cyprian. de Mort.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49116:30"/>ever. And are we ſo much Afflicted for part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them? Where is the love then, that we think we bear them? Are not ourſelves the proper Object of it; and its utmoſt Term? No doubt it is Nicknam'd-kindneſs, that would have them leave the Church Triumphant for the Militant. What? would you have them pay back their Wages; come down, and do their Work once over more? Now they have won the Field, and are dividing the Spoil, to have them run the hazard of another Battle, is certainly very far from real Friendſhip: is great Unkindneſs. It can't be Love; to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Men gotten ſafe into their Port, and with ſo rich a Cargo, ſhould be thruſt out afreſh into a Sea, moſt dangerous, and tempeſtuous. <hi>Is this our Kindneſs to our Friends?</hi> In ſhort, for them to be with us again, were to exchange their raviſhing, unſpeakable, and eternal Joys and Bliſs, for Cares, and Fears, and Pains, and Sorrows, and Sins, once more. <hi>Theſe</hi> now the Almighty Mercy hath freed them from for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: <hi>Thoſe</hi> it hath ſixed them in eternally. Canſt find in thy heart to grudge that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Kindneſs God hath ſhewed them? Muſt thou not readily ſpeak it: I am dumb; <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou, Lord, didst it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Thou,</hi> &amp;c. Thou, at whoſe hands we have deſerved abundantly worſe, than ever yet we have received. Well may we ſay with the holy Prophet, how bad ſoever it fareth with us: <hi>He hath not dealt with us after our ſins; nor
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49116:30"/>rewarded us according to our iniquities.</hi> Pſal. 103.10. Nay, the good Man <hi>Ezra</hi>'s acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be ours alſo: <hi>Our God hath puniſhed us leſs than our iniquities deſerve.</hi> Chap. 9.13. He that complains for wanting of the <hi>ſtaff of Bread,</hi> may give God thanks that the <hi>Bread of Life</hi> is not taken from him: for long ago, and too too often he made a forfeiture of his Right unto that greateſt Mercy. He that bemoans his Lameneſs, Pains and bodily Sickneſs, is Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to meer Grace, that he is not under the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting Terrors of Soul, and the Rack of a wounded Spirit: his Sins having amply merit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that, and a great while ſince. He that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth a dear Friend's being gone to Heaven, and leaving him behind on Earth; moſt juſtly may admire the Divine Goodneſs that his own Tranſgreſſions had not a great while ſince tumbled his own Body into the Grave, and his Soul to Hell. It is a ſtinging Queſtion, and ſmartly rebukes the querulous Chriſtian, which is put by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah;</hi> he asks, <hi>Wherefore doth a living man complain? A man for the puniſhment of his ſins?</hi> Lam. 3.39. We are the Fools, that make the Rod, for our own back; and may well enough be ſaid to lay it on too: for we procure the doing of it. But <hi>why do we complain;</hi> and yet the Grave hath not ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed us up? Whilſt there is life (we ſay) there's hope. And ſo there is: Hope of a Peace with God; hope of Judgment's being removed; hope of a latter End proving bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49116:31"/>than the Beginning. <hi>Why then doth a living man complain?</hi> But for a <hi>Saint,</hi> that is yet alive, and ſhall live with God for ever; <hi>Content must conquer his Complaint, and Triumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it.</hi> Thanks be to God, that pays us not in our own Coin. We rob him often of that Faith, and Hope, and Love; that Praiſe, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and Submiſſion, due to him upon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Obligations. And ſhall we murmur, when he takes but a little from us; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his own; and lent us meerly; and only till he calls for it again; as all our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts are? Surely, for very ſhame, in every trouble that happens to us, we humbly ſhould confeſs to God, that as our Duty is, <hi>We will be dumb;</hi> becauſe <hi>thou, Lord, didst it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Thou,</hi> &amp;c. Thou, that meaneſt us no hurt at all in any, thy ſevereſt Providences to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us. This Leſſon may ſeem hard, 'tis true. But <hi>if we can believe</hi> (as our Saviour ſaid) <hi>all thimgs then are poſſible,</hi> Mark 9.23. And this is very far from being improbable. The Ulcer is not lanced; no, nor the Limb cut off; with a deſign to deſtroy the Patient: but to ſave his Life. When holy <hi>David</hi> had been ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly toſs'd by a violent Tempeſt in his Thoughts, about the Proſperity of the Wicked, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of the Righteous, he happily weathers the Point at laſt; and as a Man o'er-joy'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, he can't forbear a kind of Triumph (tho' abruptly) for the great concluſion he had gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>Truly God is good to Iſrael: even to ſuch as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49116:31"/>are of a clean heart,</hi> Pſal. 73.1. Tho' he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs them: 'tis not to deſtroy them. The Surgeon, and the Soldier, both take Blood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: but He, means not to hurt, but heal; This, for no good, but killing, where he ſmites. When the Almighty's Anger lays home upon the wicked and impenitent; 'tis to make rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of them; and by a firſt, to plunge them into the ſecond Death. But Death it ſelf, the worſt of Evils, hath <hi>lost its ſting,</hi> and doth no hurt to the truly Godly ſeized by it. Then leſſer Evils are leſs <hi>likely</hi> to be for miſchief. But I ſhall come to <hi>certainty</hi> (altho but breefly, ſince ſomething near this purpoſe hath before been ſpoken:) St. <hi>Paul</hi> declares it on his knowledge, <hi>That all things work together for good to them that love God,</hi> Rom. 8.28. And Afflictions muſt be in the Number of <hi>ALL THINGS.</hi> INdeed they cheefly are reſpected by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle there. And then it cannot be too bold a Speech to ſay; The <hi>Sender</hi> of them meaneth no hurt to the Pious <hi>Bearer</hi> of them. He is not therefore to forget his Leſſon; but keep it ſtill in Mind, and readily ſpeak it with his Mouth: I am dumb: becauſe, <hi>Thou Lord, didst it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Thou,</hi> &amp;c. Even Thou, who always u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt to deal out Sufferings to thy Servants, in their due, <hi>Weight</hi> and <hi>Meaſure.</hi> For as thy Bowels do reſtran thee from adminiſtring the bitter Potion, when no bad Diſeaſe is either to be removed, or prevented: So when theſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49116:32"/>Caſes happen, and Neceſſity urgeth the giving of it; the Doſe ſhall certainly bear exact pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the dear Patient's ſtrength and caſe. That <hi>former;</hi> thine Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> doth aſſure us of, ſaying; <hi>Now for a ſeaſon (if need be;</hi> and not otherwiſe) <hi>ye are in heavineſs,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.7. Bleſſed be thy Name, Thou doſt not as ſome ill Phyſitians do: <hi>viz.</hi> make Experiments, and try Practices on them. No; no: <hi>Thou dost not afflict willingly, nor grieve the children of men,</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 3.33. Much leſs the Children of God; thine own Regenerate Off-ſpring. Then for the <hi>latter;</hi> thy Servant <hi>Paul</hi> doth make us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident; that thy Wiſe Compaſſion in thine Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations doth diſtinguiſh betwixt the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Young Men,</hi> and <hi>Little Children</hi> in thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. For he telleth us; <hi>That thou art faithful, and will not ſuffer us to be tempted above what we are able,</hi> 1 Cor. 27.8. Here is no preſcribing an Equal Quantity (hand over head) to young and old, to weak and ſtrong; as the Blind Quacks are wont to do. <hi>Eſay</hi> gave this Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence long before the Apoſtles time; when he acknowledgeth unto God touching the troubles of his People; That <hi>in meaſure, when in ſhooteth forth he would debate with it,</hi> Eſay 27.8. (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and how far agreable to their ſtate and ſtrength) and, if the caſe required, bate ſome <hi>drams,</hi> or <hi>ſcruples,</hi> or <hi>grains</hi> at leaſt: for ſaith he, <hi>Thou ſtayest thy rough wind in the day of thine east wind.</hi> Whence it is clear; either their <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> ſhall be Lighter, or their <hi>Backs</hi> made
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49116:32"/>Stronger. And then 'tis no complaining Caſe, and commands repoſe and quiet to their Minds: they muſt be dumb: becauſe <hi>thou, Lord, hast done it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10, and laſtly; <hi>Thou, Lord, didst it.</hi> Thou, O moſt Compaſſionate and Gracious Lord; who ſhortly, very ſhortly,<note place="margin">Dabit Deus his quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> finem. <hi>Virg.</hi>
               </note> wilt put a Final End, an Everlaſting Period, to all Diſtreſſes of thy Faithful Servants. It is but <hi>yet a little While;</hi> a few Moments longer, and then Adieu, and Farewel for ever; All Cares, and Fears; All Griefs, and Sorrows; All Loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Diſappointments whatſoever. Yea, and Be Gone Eternally, That <hi>Troubler</hi> of God's <hi>Iſrael;</hi> That <hi>Achan</hi> in the Camp; That <hi>Jonah</hi> in the Ship; Indwelling Sin; whoſe teeming Womb hath brought forth all our Miſeries, and will be ever breeding more: be gone for ever! And welcome, Then, All Joy and Gladneſs, Exalting and Triumphing in an Holy State of Bliſs and Glory, Unſpeakable, Inconceivable, and Eternal! <hi>You have need of Patience,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.36. And for your help thereto; remember, <hi>'Tis but a little while, and he that will come, ſhall come, and will not tarry,</hi> Verſe 37. What is an harder Service, or Apprentiſhip, to him that hath but a Month, or Week, or Day for the Expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Term? Who makes a Pother of a froſty Morning's pinching of him; when the Spring's upon us, and Summer at its heels?
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49116:33"/>A Good Man's darkeſt Night is juſt at break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up; not only into a Dawning Light; but a Glorious Sunſhine, and a Perpetual Noon. And then all frightful Storms are huſh'd by a delightful Calm; and heart-breaking Sorrows turn'd out by raviſhing Solace. Who, pray, would grudge a little pains and trouble, to put off, and exchange, his Mourning Weeds for Wedding Robes? And think it much to ſweat (perhaps) in laying by an heavy Croſs, for taking up an heavenly Crown? This is the true Chriſtian's Buſineſs in all the Troubles wherewith he now is exerciſed. Let him hold out, and labour, but a <hi>Moment</hi> longer, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17; and all his preſent Miſery ſhall end in Endleſs Happineſs; when the Proſperous Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner's Sweets ſhall be ſwallowed up in Gall and Wormwood; and that for ever. <hi>This is the Lord's doing:</hi> and ſhould <hi>be marvelous in our eyes.</hi> This ſteels the Heart of a ſuffering Saint. This blunts the Arrows; and flats the Bullets that light upon him; and makes him ſtand impene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trable. This <hi>makes him dumb, and open not his mouth in his diſtreſſes;</hi> ſave only, with profound ſubmiſſion and humility, to give God this reaſon of his ſilence: <hi>Becauſe thou, Lord, didst it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Thou,</hi> 1. Whoſe we are; 2. Who canſt do what thou pleaſeſt; 3. Who haſt left us Many, tho' taken One Mercy from us; 4. Who yet makeſt it better with us than with many our Betters; 5. Who art able to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49116:33"/>relieve ſtill, as bad as 'tis; 6. Who provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt better for our dear Friend that's gone, than, if he had ſtaid with us, we could; 7. Who juſtly might'ſt have done much wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer by us; 8. Who meaneſt no hurt in what thou haſt done; 9. Who dealeſt in weight and meaſure with thy People in their Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, always; 10. Who very ſhortly wilt put an Everlaſting Period to all their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And now, I think, my Word's made good: and you have found an Heap of Arguments in the Pſalmiſt's One. Nor is there wanting any of the Number promiſed. Nay, they perform effectually (in mine opinion) what was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken for them. However, in this I may be bold, yet with ſufficient modeſty; that from hence, and elſewhere, you have heard abundant Reaſon, For a <hi>Godly Perſon to be ſtill and ſilent, and by no means impatient under God's heaviest Hand upon him.</hi> Which was the Firſt Task in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on me.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Solution of Objections.</hi>] The next Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice I am to be engaged in, is to give Solution unto ſome Objections, which may have taken hold on Honeſt Minds againſt this Doctrine. For the paſt Endeavours juſtly may encourage us to conclude, that they have gotten down the Flames; and afford us hopes of thinking, that the Fire is out: yet, commonly, diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Souls are fill'd with troubleſom Smoke;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49116:34"/>and have thoſe Embers in them ſtill, that <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly</hi> may break out afreſh. And truly Great Afflictions are much like Great Fires; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of when Induſtry well applied hath check'd the the Futy, yet ſtill there will be Smothering ſome days after, that muſt not be neglected, but taken meet care of. Which makes me wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling (what in my power lieth) to extinguiſh every Spark; that the Pious Sufferer may have ſatisfaction unto all his Doubts and Fears; and not without <hi>eſpecial</hi> and <hi>particular</hi> Thoughts, <hi>About his loſs of Dear Relations;</hi> which uſually (above all others) lies moſt heavy on, and ſticks moſt cloſe unto, us. But let us now at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. <q>Some, upon hearing of the Premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, (it may be) will be ready to ſay: <hi>What? ſhall we then be ſtupid, and ſenſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs of our Miſery? Must the Affections be eradicated; as the Stoicks taught? May we not deeply mourn under our dreadful Evils?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer to this quarrelſom Cavil: for that's its Name: the paſt Diſcourſe never caſts its Eye that way at all. But Paſſion, when it maſters Reaſon, hurrieth Men from one Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme unto another, and will not ſuffer the Golden Mean to have their company. The <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> gives us many Inſtances of the moſt Eminent Saints that have been much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected upon their Loſſes, in point of <hi>Health,</hi> and <hi>Friends,</hi> and ſpecially of the <hi>Word of God</hi> and the <hi>Churches Peace.</hi> 'Tis true, the Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49116:34"/>of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> (to look no further) will ſhew us, they have had ſome concernment (tho of a lower ſize) about Eſtate too. But touching Sickneſs; <hi>David</hi> and <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zekiah,</hi> two Pious Princes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.5, 6, 7. Eſay 38.3.</note> have much complained. As for a Friend's deceaſe, <hi>David and all the People wept at Abner's grave.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.</note> A <hi>Brother</hi> was bewailed <hi>by Mary and Martha.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 11. Gen. 50.</note> So their Father by <hi>Jacob's Son:</hi> as he had <hi>mourn'd</hi> before for his Son <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 37.</note> The like was done, and with tears al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, by the <hi>Father of the Faithful</hi> for his Wife <hi>Sarah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 23.</note> But why ſhould I ſtay on thoſe that were Meer Men, tho truly Pious? the <hi>God-Man, Christ Jeſus, Wept</hi> for dead <hi>Lazarus,</hi> John 11.35. So that 'tis neither <hi>ſinful,</hi> nor <hi>femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> frailty, to grieve with Fears on juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. And the ſubverſion of the Temple and the Synagogue, wherein the Means of Grace, the Word and Ordinances were ſolemnly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, is grievouſly lamented by the Church of old in the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 74.7, 8.</note> Book of <hi>Pſalms.</hi> So that it is not <hi>Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſimply,</hi> is condemned; but the <hi>Manner, Meaſure,</hi> or <hi>Duration</hi> thereof, that makes it faulty.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Manner.</hi>] Touching the firſt; When the the Heart doth ſwell, the Spirit murmur, and the Thoughts repine in an Affliction: 'tis then
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49116:35"/>bad indeed! As if the <hi>Judge of all the Earth would not do right!</hi> As if <hi>his Ways were not equal!</hi> As if <hi>Iniquity could be found with him!</hi> Hainous and dreadful Guilt! Such Mourning, with Briny Tears, and a Broken Heart, is to be Mourn'd over again.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Meaſure.</hi>] As to the ſecond: Exceſs of Grief impairs both Body and Soul too; and puts the whole Man out of frame, to that degree; that he becomes unfit for Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and Man. And indeed it ſeems; not only a violating of the ſixth Commandment;<note place="margin">Thou ſhalt not kill.</note> but near a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing Chriſtianity, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Pagan.</hi> Which makes the Apoſtle bid Chriſtians, <hi>Not to ſorrow as thoſe that have no hope:</hi> meaning <hi>Heathens,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Duration.</hi>] Then for the third and laſt: <hi>There is,</hi> indeed, <hi>a Time to mourn,</hi> ſaith the Divine Preacher, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.4. And 'tis <hi>but a Time:</hi> it muſt determine; and not be for ever. To ſet the Bounds thereof, preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, may perhaps be hard. But note;<note place="margin">Gen. 27.41. &amp; 50.4, 10. Deut. 34.8. Eſay 60.20.</note> The Sacred Writ doth call them <hi>Days of Mourning;</hi> and not <hi>Years,</hi> nor <hi>Months;</hi> no, not <hi>Weeks.</hi> Which manifeſts, that we ought to keep within a great deal narrower compaſs, than many practiſe. I know,<note n="*" place="margin">Antiq. Jud. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells us; That <hi>Thirty Days was its ſtated time,</hi> among the People of God of old. And we are
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49116:35"/>more certain; that <hi>Moſes</hi> was mourn'd for juſt ſo long by the the <hi>Jews:</hi> as both himſelf, and they,<note place="margin">Deut. 34.8. Numb. 20.29.</note> had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for <hi>Aaron.</hi> Of this we may conclude; when once our mourning hinders cheerful attendance upon God, and due reſpect to Men; Its time is then expired; and it muſt determine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. <q>Alas! <hi>in my Condition,</hi> may others ſay, <hi>Having lost ſo dear a Friend, my Care, and Pains, and Prayers; my Hopes, and Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons too, are all made fruſtrate. What ſhould I do, but as once</hi> Jacob <hi>ſaid, Go down into the grave mourning?</hi>
               </q> Gen 37.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, in the Apoſtle's words upon another occaſion, <hi>I ſhew thee a more excellent way.</hi> Rebuke thy Soul, as holy <hi>Aſaph</hi> did his own; and good <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhould have alſo done; and all <hi>pious Perſons</hi> ought to do, when they are tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted to think God hath no kindneſs for them, becauſe ſeverer Providences reſt upon them: <hi>This is mine infirmity,</hi> Pſal. 77.10. 'Tis, in good truth, an Infirmity; and no little and inconſiderable Frailty, neither. It borders, at the leaſt, upon all thoſe faulty circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of that Mourning juſt now ſpoken of: it cannot plead <hi>not guilty,</hi> to the Charge of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring at God's good Pleaſure; and that too much, and too long alſo. For, is it fitting that God's Will be done, or yours? If yours; why are you Creatures, depending upon him entirely, and to be diſpoſed of by him wholly?
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49116:36"/>Nay, why do ye play the Hypocrites, and mock him daily to his face; by ſaying, <hi>Thy will be done in Earth, as 'tis in Heaven?</hi> Do not the holy Angels, and <hi>Spirits of just Men made perfect</hi> both readily do, and readily acquieſce in, what <hi>He</hi> will have done? What if they be not obnoxious to your preſent Evils; are not ye in the aſſared expectation of partaking of their good e're long?</p>
            <p>Beſides, you are under a great Miſtake. Your Care, and Pains and Prayers are not Fruſtrate: However your Hopes and Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be reckned off Becauſe God's Ends are anſwered; and they ſhould be yours. Bend but your Will; to his: and they are fulfilled As for thy Prayers, how can they be Fruſtrate; either to the Deceaſed, or unto thyſelf Survi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving? <hi>If all things work together for good to them that love God:</hi> this providence alſo muſt do ſo; <hi>Suppoſe thee ſuch.</hi> And then (to paſs by leſſer matters) Thy Friend is not (properly) Gone away; only, Gone before a little. Nor are Requeſts denyed, becauſe not anſwered as we expected. God hath a better way to grant them in, when he doth not give them to us our way. Our deareſt Lord <hi>was heard in that he feared:</hi> altho he dyed the Death, againſt which he ſo earneſtly prayed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 3.<q>  There are thoſe alſo with whom this Language is to be found.<hi>I have lost at once my dearest Friend, a comfortable Eſtate; nay, my Subſiſtance and Support. How ſhould I bound my Lamentation?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:49116:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Being taking for a Perſon fearing God, thou deſerveſt the Reproof that was given St. <hi>Peter</hi> by our Saviour: <hi>O thou of little faith; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dost thou fear? Doth man live by bread alone, and not by every word, that goeth out of the mouth of God?</hi> Matt. 4.4. <hi>whoſe is the world, and the fulneſs thereof? who feeds the fowls, and cloaths the lillies?</hi> And art thou leſs to God, than they? But there is worſe than this at bottom of this Complaint. The guile and fraud herein is plain to Man, much more to God. It is not the Friend, but what was His (it ſeems) thou doſt Bewail the loſs of. But to ſpare thee there. Who is it bids us, <hi>Take no thought for our life; no nor for our body?</hi> Matth. 6.25. Let not Anxiety ſeize us either for <hi>food,</hi> or <hi>raiment?</hi> For if our Souls be now (as they ſhould be) in Heaven; our Bodies will make good ſhift enough on Earth; never fear it. Our Gracious Lord, who cannot deceive us, bids us; <hi>Seek God's kingdom, and his righteouſneſs above all things elſe;</hi> and he hath paſs'd his Word, and is both able and willing to make it good; that <hi>all things neceſſary ſhall be added to us,</hi> Verſe 33. thrown in, as <hi>Thread and Paper</hi> at the Grocers, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting Cares about them. Nature is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with a little. And Satisfaction, Peace and Quiet with our Portion is never attained by an Addition to, but a Subſtraction from, our fond Deſires. I need not ſend theſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to that Cloud of Witneſſes recorded in the Book of God, who in their greateſt wants
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49116:37"/>could caſt their care on Him, and found ſupply enough in him. That bleſſed Name (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we all are called) although he made the World and had it wholly at his Command, and Beck, was notwithſtanding <hi>pleaſed well</hi> enough, when he <hi>had not where to lay his head,</hi> Mat. 8.20. But the Morals of a very Heathen will cry ſhame on ſuch a Chriſtian. Thence you ſhall often hear much to the purpoſe;<note n="*" place="margin">Dici potest de Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitijs, quod in Medicum glorioſum dictumest; tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um remedium morbum gravorem facit. <hi>Plut. de Cupid. divit.</hi> Is maxime divitije afflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, qui minime indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get. <hi>Sen. de Pauper.</hi> Non in Paupertate vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, ſed in Paupere, <hi>&amp;c. Id. de Remed. fort.</hi>
               </note> of contemning Wealth, and being content with a mean Eſtate. What dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger's there; and what ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty here: and therefore how far from being repined at are lower Circumſtances in the World? The Divine O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle aſſures us; <hi>That Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with Contentment is great gain.</hi> And if we be Godly, whatever Portion God ſhall allot unto us; that will certainly ſerve; and ought to pleaſe; us. And ſo this Storm is calm'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. <q>
                  <hi>The Comfort of my Life is gone;</hi> ſay others, <hi>What Counſel, Support, Refreſhment, and Encouragement,</hi> was <hi>I wont to have from the true Sympathy of ANOTHER SELF? But all is vaniſh'd, and gone for ever. And who can bear it?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And is't no Comfort, that thou ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hadſt ſuch a Comfort; and didſt ſo long injoy it? Methinks, thy cheerful Thanks for
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49116:37"/>that, ſhould ſome-what check thy doleful Moanes for this. But to deal more plainly: Is't ſo indeed? No marvel, if a <hi>Jealous God</hi> would not endure a <hi>Rival</hi> with him. His Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he is liberal of, unto his People: but <hi>his glory, he'll not give unto any other,</hi> Eſa. 42.8. We often loſe our Mercies, becauſe we dote ſo much on them, as to have God too little in our Thoughts by reaſon of them. And ſhould he like that? when Reaſon and Religion tell us; the Creator ſhould have the Throne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our Hearts: the Foot-ſtool ſerves the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture well enough. Nay, this is real kindneſs to <hi>us:</hi> that God diverts the muddy Streams, to make us run to the Cryſtal Spring. When the loving Maſter will not give the Trencher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcraps unto his honeſt Servant; but the while allows him a well-ſtor'd Larder: hath he any cauſe to take that ill? Or if an affectionate Husband liketh not to have his Pocket pick'd; whilſt he gives his Wife the Keys to take out Gold and Silver at her own diſcretion: hath ſhe cauſe to make Complaint for this? No doubt, but every good Man will ſay to God with <hi>David: All my ſprings are in thee,</hi> Pſ. 87.7. And with the Apoſtle to our Saviour: <hi>Whither ſhall we go? Thou hast the words of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life,</hi> John 6.68. Now ſuch a Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence calls aloud upon him, to haſten to his <hi>Fountain,</hi> and his <hi>Store-houſe.</hi> Indeed, ſuppoſe a Saint in this diſtreſs had not a God to go to; or were he bar'd acceſs unto his Preſence;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49116:38"/>when his deſired Comfort were gone for ever: there might, I grant, be a little pardon for his Impatience. But (bleſſed be the Lord) <hi>His Eyes</hi> are ever looking after him; <hi>His Ears</hi> ſtand always open to him; <hi>His Hands</hi> are ſtretched out continually for him; and <hi>His Heart</hi> never without yearnings towards him: and ſurely, this is ample Compenſation for, and abundant Conſolation in, the worſt Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; if People will duly apply their Souls to God. 'Tis that He aims at; and urgeth us unto. <hi>Call upon me in the time of trouble; I will deliver thee, and thou ſhalt gloriſe me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15. Pſal. 55.22. Phil. 4.6. 1 Pet. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>Cast your burden on the Lord, and he ſhall ſuſtain thee. Be careful for nothing. But caſt all your care on God.</hi> What loſs cannot he make up <hi>in Specie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Puta Deum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, quid habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quod de me queri poſſitis? <hi>Sen de Pro vid. c. 6.</hi>
               </note> if he pleaſe? And if he doth not give the <hi>Idem;</hi> the <hi>Tantundem</hi> is as good. To be ſure, tho <hi>Elkanah</hi> ask'd his Wife only; was not <hi>he better than Ten Sons?</hi> God, who is his Peoples Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in all Diſtreſſes, is better than <hi>Ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Worlds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 5. <q>But, <hi>'twas my woful Folly; or elſe mine Evils had not come upon me. That Loſs, This Sickneſs, The Other bad Accident, had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver happen'd to me, if becoming Frudence had been my Conduct. Such Means would have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented all my Miſery. Now: Woe is me, for my hard Hap!</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:49116:38"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Remember firſt: <hi>That Hap was certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God's Hand.</hi> For Fortune, Luck, and Chance,<note place="margin">— Sed te nos facimus, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna Deam, Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> locamus. <hi>Juv. Sat. 10.</hi>
               </note> are meer Heathen Deities: altho the Wiſer <hi>there</hi> did laugh thereat. The Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Wiſe, and Righteous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence governs even our Inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertencies, and Miſtakes; and directs them to the iſſue they arrive at. Nay, all Events what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, are ſo much influenced Thence, as to be <hi>Effected,</hi> or thereby <hi>Permitted.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 45.8. Acts 4.28.</note> 
               <hi>Such hand it had about the ſelling</hi> Joſeph <hi>into</hi> Egypt; <hi>and the villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Murder of the bleſſed Jeſus:</hi> that neither <hi>That</hi> nor <hi>This</hi> were brought to paſs without it. Yet wicked Men, and Devils, are the ſole Efficients of all Moral Evil. Sin is hateful unto God;<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.7. Pſal. 5.5. Hab. 1.13.</note> and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners too, who perſiſt therein; and they ſhall be puniſh'd to a ſad Eternity for the ſame. So, tho it be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Blaſphemy once to conceit it, that God is the Author of Iniquity; yet He undoubtedly ſets Bounds thereto, as to the Raging Sea; and ſaith, <hi>Hitherto ſhalt thou come, and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and here ſhall thy Proud Waves be ſtaid.</hi> Wherefore, notwithſtanding, All our Culpable Errors are to be truly, and fadly, repented of; with Supplication for God's Pardon: yet we may not overlook his Hand in order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them to their Iſſue. Under which, <hi>being humbled duly, we may expect ſeaſonably to be lifted up,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.6.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:49116:39"/>
            <p>But moſt eſpecially; let's never forget the Leſſon that our bleſſed Saviour taught his moſt dear Diſciples: That <hi>not one of the poor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10.29.</note> 
               <hi>little, and</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Magna hic em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis Diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivi. <hi>Bez.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>deſpicable Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows fell to the ground without our Father:</hi> his Licenſe, Order, or Appointment, that is: <hi>Fear ye not therefore; ye are of more value than many Sparrows,</hi> Verſ. 31. is our dear Lord's Inference thence. And ſo we may conclude; That the moſt unhappy Accidents, in Eſtate, Health, Relations, or any other way; are of God's wiſe and good ſufferance, or ſending, to us. Then, as for the Lives of the Saints of God: if <hi>their Hairs be all numbred,</hi> v. 30. and <hi>their Death be precious in his ſight,</hi> Pſ. 116.15; as both are certain; with what exactneſs will he keep the reckning of their Abode on Earth? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no ſingle Day, nor Hour, nor Minute, ſhall careleſly, or caſually, be caſt away. Yea, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; not only <hi>our times are in God's hand,</hi> Pſal. 31.15; but <hi>our days are determined, and the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our months are with the Lord: our bounds are appointed, which we cannot paſs,</hi> Job 14.5. And then we need not fear, but that we ſhall reach up thereto: whatever may be thought unto the contrary. Indeed, the <hi>Will of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi> in the Lord is unknown to us, until the Event declares it. And 'tis our Duty, only to attend his <hi>Will of Precept.</hi> We muſt uſe lawful Means which he approves: yet be content, that the Almighty's pleaſure be effected by them.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:49116:39"/>
            <p>And as for <hi>Means</hi> ſuggeſted to be omitted; Either it was really ſo; or not. If not: how childiſh is it, to complain for nothing? If ſo: 'twas either through thy fault, or not. If this; <hi>Not through thy fault:</hi> (And how unlikely is it, that the fear of God, and love of one ſo dear, would ſuffer Means to be omitted wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully?) Suppoſe it thine Unhappineſs; 'tis not thy Sin; and ſhould not be thy Torment. Therefore ſuch Fears and Jealouſies, which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten overcome afflicted Spirits, muſt be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and baniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 6. <q>Some yet may ſay: <hi>But I am ignorant of God's meaning towards me, in his heavy Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. And what to do, but Mourn, I know not.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Admit, thou art to ſeek therein: wil't make thy ſelf yet more uncapable to find it out? This is the readieſt way of all thereto: Exceſſive Grief both blinds and deafs the Soul at once. And what is to be ſeen, in Midnight-darkneſs: or heard, at the Cataracts of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus;</hi> or by the beating of a Drum? Thou rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Clouds, and makeſt Clamours within thy Boſom, that put thee to confuſion and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. Be therefore Maſter of thy ſelf in patience, and thou mak'ſt it poſſible to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to purpoſe. Whil'ſt <hi>Job</hi> was in this Hurry, he ſaith indeed to God: <hi>Shew me, wherefore thou contendest with me,</hi> Job 10.2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But this came from ſuch diſcontent, that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd without its Errand. Tho afterwards,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49116:40"/>when he came fully to himſelf, and dealeth in a quiet, humble, and ſubmiſſive way with God; <hi>abhorring himſelf</hi> for his paſt fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs and impatience;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job 42.6,</hi> &amp;c. per tot.</note> 
               <hi>and repenting in dust and aſhes;</hi> he quickly meets with bleſt ſucceſs, unto abundant ſatisfaction: as may be read in the Chapter quoted in the Margin.</p>
            <p>Obſerve beſide; it is no eaſie matter, <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily;</hi> and doubtleſs, <hi>oftentimes,</hi> impoſſible, to aſſign the ſpecial Meſſage of ſuch, or ſuch a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer Providence toward thoſe that truly ſear the Lord. 'Tis true, it ſometimes happens, that the Judgments carry ſuch viſible Tokens of the Sins that ſent them, written as it were in Capital Letters on them; that it becomes no difficulty to underſtand the ſpecial Errand that they bring. You ſaw it the Caſe of Holy <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Example <hi>4. Supra.</hi>
               </note> ſpoken of before. But commonly, and for the moſt part, as I ſaid, 'tis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. And the Pious, in affliction; if they find not full ſatisfaction, in our Saviour's words to <hi>Peter,</hi> ſpoken of before; <hi>What I do, thou knowest not now; but ſhalt know afterwards:</hi> yet I am very confident, that under the ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, darkeſt, and moſt uncouth Providence; <hi>let them nut loath themſelves in their own ſight for all their offences; be numbled under the mighty Hand of God; run to the Fountain open'd for Sin and for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs; die more unto the World, and lay up their Treaſure, and Heart too, more in Heaven;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49116:40"/>have none but God</hi> Above; <hi>and God above all</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; <hi>unto them:</hi> Let them make this their Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs under their ſaddeſt Sufferings, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere thereat: And moſt undoubtedly, as God obtains his End, they ſhall not miſs his Mind. Thus all Afflictions ſhall ſerve his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Glory; and ſurely iſſue in their greateſt Good.</p>
            <p>And then; I conclude with confidence; This will not only ſtill a diſtreſſed Saint; but turn his weeping into laughter, and put off his Sackeloth for more beautiful Garments; and exchange his Lamentations into Songs of Praiſes unto the God of his Salvation; who <hi>commandeth light to ſhine forth out of darkneſs,</hi> and will bring Good from Evil, to them <hi>are good and upright in heart before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The laſt Thing undertaken was; <hi>Some Guidance for the better Application of the whole un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelves for good.</hi> And this I ſhall diſpatch in theſe two or three following Inferences:</p>
            <p>Infer. 1. Since it is ſo, <hi>That,</hi> &amp;c. Then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, pious People muſt not expect all Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon Days on Earth; nor flatter themſleves with hopes of a Summer that ſhall laſt their life, without any ſtorm or cloud attending it: but they muſt reckon on't, and be content, to take their ſhare of trouble that happens to them. How otherwiſe, could it be a Duty on them; <hi>To be quiet in Diſtreſſes, if none ſhould ever reach them?</hi> Aſſure your ſelves; that tho Beſt Chriſtians be not in all reſpects <hi>True La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi>'s:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49116:41"/>yet muſt they, with Him, expect to have their <hi>Evil things here:</hi> and happy are they, that they ſhall be ſure of their <hi>Good here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi> A Traveller in a ſtrange Country, far diſtant from his Native Soil: A Mariner ſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a long and dangerous Voyage on the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean: and eſpecially, a Soldier, that hath a Crafty, Cruel, and Powerful Enemy to conteſt withal, muſt not befool himſelf with hopes of Eaſe, and Reſt, and Quiet, and his Heart's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, without all thoughts of trouble ever coming near him. This were ſo ſilly a <hi>Self-Flattery;</hi> as muſt at laſt make Men to rue it ſadly with too late Repentance. Are we not going out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and through the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, towards the Heavenly <hi>Canaan?</hi> Is not this World, wherein we all are lanched, more like the Earth ſurrounding <hi>Main,</hi> than the Three Leagues Red Sea which <hi>Iſrael</hi> paſſed through? And are not the Devil, World, and Fleſh, All mortal Foes unto us, and of too much ſtrength to do us miſchief? Can we be free from trouble then? Nor is this any juſt diſcouragement unto ſerious Piety; as he well knows that hath not loſt already the things before diſcourſed on at large. It only ſerves to make us ſtand unto our Arms, that we be not ſurpriſed; and whets our Courage, the better to ingage the Difficulties that we meet with. Our bleſſed Saviour never meant to drive Men from him; when he tells them plainly, That they <hi>ſhould count their Coſt;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49116:41"/>to <hi>bear their Croſs, and follow him; as they would be his Diſciples,</hi> Luke 14.27, 28, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Goſpel gives moſt full Aſſurance; and experienc'd Chriſtians know right well; that true RELIGION weighs <hi>down to the ground</hi> whatever Inconveniences lye in the Scale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. Nor is there any Compariſon to be made, <hi>betwixt the ſufferings of this preſent time, in an holy courſe; and the glory that ſhall ſucceed hereafter,</hi> Rom. 8.18. The Proportion is much nearer betwixt loſing a Braſs Counter, for gaining of Ten hundred thouſand Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea's. And what a Bargain worth the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving is That? But ſtill; a Chriſtian's Life is a Continual Warfare. Suppoſe there be a preſent Truce: who knoweth but that a few hours hence it may be broken? And if we are ſurpriſed then at unawares; of how <hi>great</hi> dammage may it prove unto us: if not <hi>irreparable?</hi> Look therefore for Afflictions, if thou be truly Godly; not with a <hi>fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> but a <hi>fixed</hi> Mind. Look for them ſo; and whenſoever they come, they will not then look ghaſtly on thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infer.</hi> 2. <hi>Since,</hi> &amp;c. Then the worſt of Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings that can befal God's Servants are not ſo terrible as the World doth commonly reckon; and perhaps, the Sufferers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, may take them for. This followeth plainly: becauſe, that Wiſe and Gracious God, who looks for nothing from his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49116:42"/>but what's moſt juſt and equal, doth yet expect, that they ſhould be <hi>ſedate</hi> and <hi>quiet</hi> under all Diſtreſſes. Wherefore they cannot, duly, be accounted as amazing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies, and monſtrous Portents. Indeed there is no Affliction but is grievous in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And many go a great deal nearer to the quick, than others do. Yet ſtill; the very worſt upon a pious Perſon hath not <hi>Plague-Tokens</hi> with it: is not Incurably Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. He <hi>that hath ſwallowed up Death in Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> Eſay 25.8. gives us encouragement to ſay of the very worſe of their Diſeaſes; <hi>This Sickneſs is not unto Death,</hi> John 11. I mean not,<note place="margin">Tantu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> interest non qualia, ſed qualis, quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> patiatur. <hi>S. Aug. de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. D. 1.8.</hi>
               </note> as to <hi>Temporal:</hi> but 'tis not, to <hi>Eternal</hi> Death. For the plain truth is: for ſuch, to <hi>die on Earth,</hi> is nothing elſe, but to <hi>live in Heaven for ever.</hi> Then no Diſtreſs, whatever it is, can be truly <hi>deadly</hi> to him that lives in Chriſt. No: as the Hand that gives the ſtroke, is ever ſet on work, and guided too, by Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Love and Wiſdom: ſo likewiſe, there is the <hi>Good Samaritan</hi> always ſtanding by, and ready to apply the <hi>Balm of Gilead</hi> with tender Pity, and ſure Succeſs. I know, that a wicked and malignant World, inſpired from Hell, and thruſt on by the Devil thereof, will make what havock they are able on God's People; and then erect their Trophies, and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49116:42"/>Triumph upon the Spoils that by themſelves are made. Yea, tho their own Life doth vouch themſelves ſworn Vaſſals unto Satan; yet under ſuch Calamities, they will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Righteous but <hi>Meer Pretenders un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</hi> And this, they count, is perfect proof thereof: in that they think, they have them at their own Mercy; whoſe <hi>Mercies,</hi> we are ſure, <hi>are</hi> very <hi>Cruelty.</hi> The Man after God's heart could fare no better at their hands. <hi>His Enemies, that lay in wait for his Soul, took coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel together, and ſpake thus against him: God hath forſaken him: for there is none to deliver him,</hi> Pſal. 71.10, 11. But their Meaſures fail'd them there: as they will do elſewhere, upon like occaſion. The laſt Verſe faith, <hi>They are confounded; they are brought to ſhame, that ſeek my hurt.</hi> The Wicked, are <hi>God's Staff</hi> indeed: yea, and they are <hi>his Rod.</hi> And how frequent (if not conſtant) is it; for the merciful Providence to break that <hi>Staff,</hi> and burn that <hi>Rod,</hi> wherewith his Children had been ſmitten? Sure I am; that the Proud and Powerful King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> (altho he feared no ſuch matter) was forc'd to feel it, <hi>Eſay</hi> 10. And neither Turk, nor French, nor Pope, can hope for better; when the <hi>Seaſon</hi> is. Faith then ſhould baniſh Fear; and ſuffer Terror to take no hold upon us. Improve <hi>That;</hi> and 'twill be able to ſcorn <hi>the ſury of the Oppreſſor, Eſay</hi> 51.12, 13; tho Earth and Hell, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49116:43"/>abet him. Nay, and All other Evils, that may happen, <hi>then,</hi> cannot be <hi>diſmal</hi> to us. If <hi>neither Life nor Death; not Angels, Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, nor Powers; neither preſent things, nor fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor height, nor depth, nor any Creature, can ſeparate the truly Pious from the love of God in Christ,</hi> Romans 8.38, 39. What ſhould be greatly Terrible and Affrighting to them? I may therefore well conclude with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter</hi>'s Charge; <hi>That none of us think it ſtrange, concerning the ſeverest Providences; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ſhould be a fiery Tryal; as if ſome ſtrange thing happened to us,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.12. For a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian's Sufferings, whatever they are, cannot ſeem Uncouth and Horrid Matters; if our paſt Diſcourſe be well conſidered by us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infer.</hi> 3. Since, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then in the laſt place: it ought to be the care and labour of us All, in all our ſad'ſt Conditions, to acquit our ſelves, not only as <hi>God;s Creatures,</hi> but as <hi>good Chriſtians alſo:</hi> i. <hi>to be ſtill and quiet under the ſeverest Providences of God.</hi> Being the <hi>Work of his Hands;</hi> All that we have and are is his own, and due to him; both when, and how, he will pleaſe to call for it. But, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the Price of his Blood</hi> too: his Right is double; and there can be no diſpute; but that we are, and ought to be moſt abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and moſt righteouſly, at his Diſpoſal. But I ſhall not ſtay on Arguments to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade hereto; being fully of opinion, that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49116:43"/>thoſe on whom the former Diſcourſes will not have ſufficient Influence to convince them of their Duty in the point; neither would they believe themſelves obliged, <hi>ſhould a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger from the Dead come, and acquaint them with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All I ſhall therefore further meddle with at preſent will be, to do what ſervice I am cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of, in giving the beſt Directions, that I can, for our more ready Obedience unto God in this important Buſineſs; <hi>Of being ſtill and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent under the greatest troubles that befal us.</hi> There are but three or four (though many more are ready) that I ſhall inſiſt upon: and they are theſe,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direct.</hi> 1. Make ſure, thy Soul be furniſhed with effectual, and ſaving Grace: that thou be not barely an Appendant <hi>unto Jeſus Christ,</hi> but implanted <hi>into him;</hi> and haſt devoted thy ſelf entirely to him. Then, being found a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in Sincerity: either there is little danger of thy being plunged into that Gulf; or great preſumption of ſpeedy getting out again. But otherwiſe, there are no hopes of ſpecial Help from Heaven. I grant, indeed, if any People have attain'd to Stoical <hi>Apathy,</hi> or are the Maſters of the ancient <hi>Roman</hi> Gallantry (as 'tis called); they then may <hi>ſeem</hi> to out-brave the worſt of Evils on them, with a quiet and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reſolution. But, alas! 'tis nothing ſo, at all. The Principle, whereby the former is
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49116:44"/>acted, puts of <hi>true Man;</hi> and what moves the latter is an utter ſtranger to the <hi>true God.</hi> And neither of them deſerve the Name of <hi>true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Fortitude;</hi> but indeed of a <hi>fool-hardy deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Stupidity.</hi> The Chriſtian Valour neither raſhly courts a Miſery, nor declines it baſely: but being come, as it feels the ſmart, ſo it knows who ſent it: and that much worſe was well deſerved; but yet, this coming on a gracious Errand, it bears up under it, with out Repining at it; and waiteth quietly a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Deliverance from it, and great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by it. But now, this Herb grows not in the Common-fields of Chriſtianity. 'Tis not the <hi>High-way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 13. Luke 8.</note> nor the <hi>Thorny,</hi> nor the <hi>Stony Ground</hi> will bring it kindly forth. No: it muſt be a <hi>good and honest Heart,</hi> made ſo by ſpecial Grace, where it arriveth to perſection. If thou haſt now a bare <hi>Name to live when thou art dead;</hi> and takeſt up with <hi>a form of Godlineſs, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the power thereof;</hi> there are no hopes, thou ſhouldſt have help, and be kept ſteddy when violent Winds and Waves aſſault thee. But if Religion be thy Buſineſs; the biaſs of thy Heart be Heaven-ward; and Jeſus Chriſt be the Loadſtone that thy Soul ſtands to, and only ſixeth at; why <hi>then,</hi> as thou art Upright with thy God, thou alſo art become even <hi>God's Delight,</hi> Prov. 11.20. Now <hi>unto the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright there ariſeth light in darkneſs;,</hi> Pſ. 112.4. The
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49116:44"/>reaſon is, <hi>Light is ſown</hi> (by the ſure Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) <hi>for him; and gladneſs for the upright in heart,</hi> Pſalm 97.11. And what God ſows, muſt ſure grow up, and ſoon be ripe too. Wherefore we are called on, to <hi>look upon it,</hi> as that which never faileth to our Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Mark the perfect Man, and behold the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: for the end</hi> (however his beginning, or middle time ſhall prove) <hi>of that Man ſhall be peace,</hi> Pſal. 37.37. And all know, 'tis <hi>the End crowns all.</hi> O that we, every one, would rouze up our Souls from a <hi>luke-warm Temper;</hi> and by no means ſettle under the leaves of a bare Profeſſion, without the power of a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Principle of Holineſs in our Hearts, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways making Heaven-ward whence <hi>it</hi> came. This would ſo ſix us on the Rock, that tho' the Tempeſts ſhake, they ſhould never over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, us. We are certainly elſe upon <hi>a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy bottom;</hi> and that hath no ſecurity. How can we ſtand in an evil Day, of Life, or Death, or Judgement; except we are thus provided? Think ſadly of the woful Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment to the <hi>fooliſh Virgins; that had their lamps indeed, but had no oil; and were ſhut out, when they thought ſure of entring in,</hi> Mat 25.10. And that thou maiſt fare better, truſt not in outward Form; but get the Truth, and Life of Grace, which God alone approveth: and thou art ſafe.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:49116:45"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Direct.</hi> 2. Be not indulgent to thy fleſh, let not thine earthly Tabernacle be too much cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er'd, and fondled by thee. 'Tis not intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here to prohibit Men from running out into <hi>exceſs of Riot,</hi> and following of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Courſes of the Debauchees of the Evil Age we live in. No: <hi>thoſe Spots are not the Spots of the Children of God;</hi> to whom I now am ſpeaking. They are the manifeſt Brand-mark ſet upon the Herd belonging to the Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs Pit. <hi>Who think it ſtrange,</hi> and <hi>ſpeak evil of the others; becauſe they will not be as vile that way as themſelves are,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.4. But what I plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mean is; that Chriſtians, who will bear Diſtreſſes to the beſt advantage, ſhould not allow themſelves unto the utmoſt Bounds of Chriſtian-liberty, in things that are ſo far from being ſimply evil, that they are indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent; yea, good and neceſſary in the due uſe thereof. Such are both Reſt and Labour, Meats and Drinks, Habits and lawful Recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations; with other things like theſe. He that treads upon the very Line of ſome large Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, may ſoon ſtep over. 'Tis very dangerous to run upon the Edge of the Bank, leaſt ye fall into the Brook. <hi>All that is lawful, is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.12. the Apoſtle teacheth. Moderate Sleep and Exerciſe refreſh Nature, and preſerve Health: but exceſs, in <hi>that</hi> brings fuel to Corruption; and in <hi>this</hi> conſumes the Spirit. The ſober uſe of wholeſom and meet
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49116:45"/>Food and Liquors is neceſſary to our ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: but Intemperance, in Delicacies and Varieties ſpecially, brings Sickneſs and Death. So Cloathing hides our Nakedneſs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth from the God: but Garriſh and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Faſhions are a Vanity full of Michief to ourſelves and others. Nay, Recreation, that ſhould be only uſed to ſit for Buſineſs; how often being exceſſive doth it untune for that, and rob us too of our choiceſt Jewel, <hi>Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Time?</hi> And yet amongſt good People, ſome may be found (I wiſh the Number were much ſmaller) that are ſo coy and delicate; that nothing but the <hi>best,</hi> and <hi>most</hi> of every thing will content them. Nay, and 'tis ſo; that the Sun muſt not ſhine, nor the Wind blow, nor the Rain drop on ſome of Them! Theſe are the ways ſo to Emaſculate poor Peoples Souls, that the lighteſt load is able to ſink them to the ground. And how ſhould great Diſtreſſes then be <hi>born;</hi> and ſtood up under, with ſuch an even and fixed Reſolution as they ought? The holy Apoſtle doth indeed allow <hi>a little Wine for the ſtomack's ſake, and for thoſe infirmities</hi> of that good Man, whoſe drink was nothing elſe <hi>but Water,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.23. But otherwiſe the ſelf-ſame Perſon he calls upon, to <hi>endure hardneſs, and as a good ſoldier,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.3. Are we not all Chriſt's Souldiers: and if we will be good Souldiers; muſt we not follow, and be like unto our Leader? O how
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49116:46"/>unlikre him, do we acquit our ſelves; who court this World, which he ſo ſcorn'd and trampled on; and pamper the Body, which he made drudge of to the Soul, and in God's ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice! Is't probable, at this rate, when Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Sickneſs, Perſecution, or Death aſſault, (and how near any of them may be to us, who can tell?) we ſhould be <hi>dumb and open not our mouth,</hi> ſubmitting quietly to his Father's Hand, as he did conſtantly? At leaſt, let's labour to tread in his Apoſtle's ſteps; <hi>keep under our body,</hi> (as it were by Club-law) <hi>and bring it into ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.27: that the vain Fancies, and ſond Appetites there may be reſtrain'd and curb'd; and our Souls may faſten and abide on what will fully ſatisfie them, and never can be rifled from them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direct.</hi> 3. <hi>Lay not thy treaſure up, on earth; but in the heavens,</hi> Matth. 6.19. Excellent Counſel of our bleſſed Lord! <hi>For where the Treaſure is, there will the Heart (i.</hi> the Man himſelf) <hi>be alſo.</hi> And if a Man hath once his Heart: <hi>viz.</hi> his Love, Delight, Deſire, and Hopes, as high as Heaven, with God and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt above; he can't be ſo concern'd with any Diſaſter here below, as to be diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd greatly by the ſame. As he that look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth down from ſome high Steeple, ſees every thing beneath him but as a ſmall and little matter: ſo Earthly Good and Bad muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily ſeem to one, <hi>whoſe Converſation is in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49116:46"/>Heaven.</hi> 'Tis certain, that there are thoſe Mountains in the World, whoſe tops will be ſerene, and clear, and calm; when Thunder, Storms, and Lightning, threaten to mix Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth together at the lower parts thereof. Could we take off our Affection from things Below, to ſet, and always keep them upon what's Above: how ſhould we live as in a conſtant Sun-ſhine?<note place="margin">Nihil erus ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit in nervo, cum animus in caelo est <hi>Tert. ad Mart. cap. 2.</hi>
               </note> When Peſtilence, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Sword, ſhould range the Earth; when Poverty, Sickneſs, Death, ſhould knock at our own Doors; how little would the Diſturbance be unto us? Poor <hi>Archimedes</hi> was ſo intent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Mathematical Studies, that he knew not when his City was ſtorm'd, and taken. And, verily, as Chriſtian, that gets his Heart full bent towards Heaven will find the diſtracting Hurries of the Earth ſlip over him with but little obſervation by him. The holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was certified by the Holy Ghoſt, in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry City he paſs'd through, <hi>that bonds and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions waited for him at Jeruſakm,</hi> and yet he faith, <hi>none of thoſe things ſo much as moved him,</hi> Acts 20.24. The <hi>Joy in finiſhing his Courſe,</hi> and the Reward after it, made even <hi>his life it ſelf,</hi> tho likely to be loſt, but a little matter with him. We are very ſure, that <hi>Moſes</hi> refuſed being a King's Grandſon, and choſe rather an afflicted ſtate with the People of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49116:47"/>God, than <hi>ſinful Pleaſures</hi> in a Prince's Court: valuing the <hi>Reproach for Christ</hi> as a Better E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate than the Exchequer of <hi>Egypt,</hi> Heb 11.24, 25, 26. But what was that which betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo wiſe and good a Man into ſuch a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, <hi>in the World's Opinion?</hi> Why, let them think ſo ſtill: but his Judgment was truly Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, notwithſtanding. <hi>For he had reſpect unto the recompence of reward,</hi> Verſe 26, <hi>fin.</hi> And <hi>ſure,</hi> to be Heir apparent unto the Crown of <hi>Egypt,</hi> deſerves not to be compared with an undoubted Title to God's Kingdom. And the Delights in Heaven are ſo ſurpaſſing, that all Earthly Joys are not inſipid only, but nauſeous, fulſome; Carrion and Poiſon, to them. Which having his Heart affected with, by a Believing Proſpect thereof; what was't to him, to throw off the Courtier, and take up the Clown? Nay, worſe? To skulk and hide a while for ſcaping of thoſe Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds that were hunting after him? And, at the laſt, to flee his Country, and abide thoſe many dangers and diſtreſſes that attend a Baniſh'd Outlaw?<note place="margin">Seculi hujus quem non deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit proſperit as non frangit ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſit as. <hi>S. Aug. de verb. Dom. Serm. 42.</hi>
               </note> All that the Earth could do againſt him, you ſee, how little 'twas unto him; becauſe his Treaſure was in Heaven: <hi>he had reſpect to the recompence of reward.</hi> Were Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians heartily making after him; although they ſhould not fully
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49116:47"/>overtake him; how light and eaſie would their many great and heavy Burdens lye upon them? To conclude; The <hi>Author and Finiſher of our Faith, for the Joy above, that was ſet before him, endured the pain, and deſpiſed the ſhame of the Bloody Croſs, whereon he ſuffer'd,</hi> Heb. 12.2. And would the Chriſtian duly look to Chriſt, he ſurely, would be like him, much more than he is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direct.</hi> 4. Laſtly: Let Sin be more uneaſie, and be ſure thy Sufferings then will be eaſier far. Wert thou worſe able to endure Corruptions, thou would'ſt be better to abide Afflictions. When once Iniquity is our greateſt Burden; all others will be little felt. The very reaſon why Diſtreſſes ſometimes triumph is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have not made a Conqueſt over our Tranſgreſſions. They are theſe that bring Tribulations to us: and make them ſit more heavy on us, when they are come. Guilt is a moſt heavy Load to an Awarkened Mind; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Another's Eye ſhould not be able to eſpy ſo much as a light Feather on its back. But the weight muſt needs be much increaſed, when Actual Puniſhment cleaveth unto Guilt. Whether the good Woman of <hi>Zarephath</hi>'s words, ſpoken to the Prophet; (<hi>Art thou come to call may Sins to remembrance; and to ſlay my Son?</hi> 1 King. 17.18.) do not imply; that a freſh cognizance took by Conſcience of her faultineſs towards God, had imbittered the Affliction to her; tho it ſeem probable; I will
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49116:48"/>not determine. But it is very plain; that This <hi>added</hi> Chains (as I may call them) to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren: For their open Confeſſion is: <hi>We are verily guilty concerning our Brother; in that we ſaw the anguiſh of his Soul, when he beſought us, and we would not hear. THEREFORE IS THIS DISTRESS COME <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PON <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> Gen. 42.21. Whence it muſt follow: would we be more Innocent, we ſhould be leſs Unhappy: moſt certainly; our Miſery would pinch and gall us leſs. What made our bleſſed Lord ſo Eaſy, Patient, and Submiſſive, in thoſe worſt of Evils upon him? Verily; becauſe He had the beſt of Souls with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Him. No Sin had ever thouched it: and how ſhould Sorrow fetch Blood from it? O, let us <hi>grow in Grace;</hi> and then our bitter Cup ſhall have no Dregs to touch our Lips. Thoſe are reſerved for the <hi>Graceleſs Ones; to wring them, out, and drink them up,</hi> Pſ. 75.8. But thriving Chriſtians, tho' they muſt have Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, ſhall not ſink under them. Such <hi>wait upon the Lord</hi> to purpoſe: and ſo <hi>renew their ſtrength.</hi> They are enabled <hi>to walk without fainting; and run and not be weary,</hi> Iſa. 40.31. Wherefore <hi>abound ye in the work of God, and your labour will not be in vain,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.58. Not only, by a more diligent Attendance on all Ordinances; but eſpecially, about increaſing Faith, inſlaming Love, confirming Hope, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting Patience, and ſetting, and keeping the whole Heart on Heaven. This would advance
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49116:48"/>the Spirit to its due Soveraignty; and reduce the Fleſh to juſt Subjection. And what can bring Diſorders then? This will draw back Sin's Fuel; and then its Fire goeth out, of itſelf. But the neglect hereof, is throwing off our Armour, inſtead of girding it cloſe about us: and then we are eaſily Shot, ands fall.</p>
            <p>Meer Nature, with all the ſtrength that Reaſon brings it, proves a weak Creature; at the laſt however. But Grace, and when like <hi>David waxing ſtronger and ſtronger,</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes all Difficulties in the way to Glory. And tho' a <hi>Pharoah</hi> be behind, a Sea before, and a Wilderneſs on both ſides; it will bear up the Soul until it <hi>ſee the Salvation of its God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sum of all my Advice is this: 1. Make ſure of Saving Grace, and being Right at Heart: 2. Be not indulgent to the Fleſh, nor fond upon thy Earthly Tabernacle: 3. Lay not thy Treaſure up on Earth, but in the Heavens, and let thy Heart be with it there: 4. Laſtly; Let Sin be more Uneaſie to thee, and thy Sufferings will be eaſier far. Grow but in Grace, and thou ſhalt Out-grow all Grief that can poſſibly ſeize thee here. For Then, thou wilt be the fulleſt Eccho to the Pſalmiſt: <hi>I was dumb; I opened not my mouth: becauſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49116:49"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for and Sold by <hi>J. Salusbury,</hi> at the <hi>Riſing-Sun</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Royal-Exchange</hi> in <hi>Coruhill.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Harmony of the Divine Attributes, in the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance and Accompliſhment of Man's Redemption, by the Lord Jeſus Christ, by <hi>William Bates, D. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Changeableneſs of this World, with reflect to Nations, Families, and particular Perſons; with a Practieal Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f, to the various Conditions of this Mortal Life, by <hi>Timothy Rogers, M. A.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Mirror for Athieſts, being ſome Paſſages of the Life and Death of the Right Honourable <hi>John</hi> Earl of <hi>Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> written by his own Direction on his Death-bed, by <hi>Gilbert Burnet</hi> Lord Ep. of <hi>Sarum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An end of Doctrinal Controverſies, which have lately troubled the Churches, by <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Certainty of the Worlds of Spirits; fully evinced by unqueſtionable Hiſtories of Apparitions and Witchcrafts; Voices proving the Immortality of Souls, by <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Proteſtant Religion truly Stated and Juſtified: by the late reverend Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter,</hi> prepared for the Preſs; ſometime before his Death. Whereunto is added, ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the learned Author, by Mr. <hi>Daniel Willams</hi> and Mr. <hi>Matthew Sylveſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Chriſtian's Coverſe with God: or, the Inſufficiency of Haman-friendſhip, and the Improvements of Solitude in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with God; with ſome of the Author's breathings after him, by <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi> Recemmended to the Readers ſerious Thoughts, when at the Houſe of Mourning and in Retirement, by Mr. <hi>Matthew Sylveſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Mourners Memorial, in two Sermons, on the Death of the truly Pious Mrs. <hi>Suſannah Soame,</hi> with ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of her Life and Death, by <hi>Timothy Wright</hi> and <hi>Robert Fleming.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49116:49"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
